<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Return xmlns="http://www.irs.gov/efile" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.irs.gov/efile" returnVersion="2022v5.0">
  <ReturnHeader binaryAttachmentCnt="0">
    <ReturnTs>2023-12-21T09:38:29-06:00</ReturnTs>
    <TaxPeriodEndDt>2023-06-30</TaxPeriodEndDt>
    <PreparerFirmGrp>
      <PreparerFirmEIN>411360831</PreparerFirmEIN>
      <PreparerFirmName>
        <BusinessNameLine1Txt>OLSEN THIELEN &amp; CO LTD</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
      </PreparerFirmName>
      <PreparerUSAddress>
        <AddressLine1Txt>2675 LONG LAKE ROAD</AddressLine1Txt>
        <CityNm>ROSEVILLE</CityNm>
        <StateAbbreviationCd>MN</StateAbbreviationCd>
        <ZIPCd>551131117</ZIPCd>
      </PreparerUSAddress>
    </PreparerFirmGrp>
    <ReturnTypeCd>990</ReturnTypeCd>
    <TaxPeriodBeginDt>2022-07-01</TaxPeriodBeginDt>
    <Filer>
      <EIN>412008684</EIN>
      <BusinessName>
        <BusinessNameLine1Txt>COMMUNITIES ORGANIZING FOR HAITIAN</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        <BusinessNameLine2Txt>ENGAGEMENT AND DEVELOPMENT</BusinessNameLine2Txt>
      </BusinessName>
      <BusinessNameControlTxt>COMM</BusinessNameControlTxt>
      <PhoneNum>6517056247</PhoneNum>
      <USAddress>
        <AddressLine1Txt>PO BOX 4094</AddressLine1Txt>
        <CityNm>SAINT PAUL</CityNm>
        <StateAbbreviationCd>MN</StateAbbreviationCd>
        <ZIPCd>55104</ZIPCd>
      </USAddress>
    </Filer>
    <BusinessOfficerGrp>
      <PersonNm>JERRY FENNER</PersonNm>
      <PersonTitleTxt>TREASURER</PersonTitleTxt>
      <PhoneNum>6517056247</PhoneNum>
      <SignatureDt>2023-12-14</SignatureDt>
      <DiscussWithPaidPreparerInd>1</DiscussWithPaidPreparerInd>
    </BusinessOfficerGrp>
    <SigningOfficerGrp>
      <PersonFullName>
        <PersonFirstNm>JERRY</PersonFirstNm>
        <PersonLastNm>FENNER</PersonLastNm>
      </PersonFullName>
      <SSN>999009999</SSN>
    </SigningOfficerGrp>
    <IRSResponsiblePrtyInfoCurrInd>0</IRSResponsiblePrtyInfoCurrInd>
    <PreparerPersonGrp>
      <PreparerPersonNm>RYAN VETTRUS CPA</PreparerPersonNm>
      <PTIN>P01243596</PTIN>
      <PhoneNum>6514834521</PhoneNum>
    </PreparerPersonGrp>
    <AdditionalFilerInformation>
      <TrustedCustomerGrp>
        <TrustedCustomerCd>2</TrustedCustomerCd>
        <AuthenticationAssuranceLevelCd>AAL1</AuthenticationAssuranceLevelCd>
        <IdentityAssuranceLevelCd>IAL1</IdentityAssuranceLevelCd>
      </TrustedCustomerGrp>
    </AdditionalFilerInformation>
    <TaxYr>2022</TaxYr>
    <BuildTS>2023-04-26 12:10:37Z</BuildTS>
  </ReturnHeader>
  <ReturnData documentCnt="9">
    <IRS990 documentId="RetDoc1038000001" referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1044400001">
      <PrincipalOfficerNm>NICAISE AVIGNON</PrincipalOfficerNm>
      <USAddress>
        <AddressLine1Txt>PO BOX 4094</AddressLine1Txt>
        <CityNm>SAINT PAUL</CityNm>
        <StateAbbreviationCd>MN</StateAbbreviationCd>
        <ZIPCd>55104</ZIPCd>
      </USAddress>
      <GrossReceiptsAmt>482696</GrossReceiptsAmt>
      <GroupReturnForAffiliatesInd>0</GroupReturnForAffiliatesInd>
      <Organization501c3Ind>X</Organization501c3Ind>
      <WebsiteAddressTxt>WWW.COFHED.ORG</WebsiteAddressTxt>
      <TypeOfOrganizationCorpInd>X</TypeOfOrganizationCorpInd>
      <FormationYr>2001</FormationYr>
      <LegalDomicileStateCd>MN</LegalDomicileStateCd>
      <ActivityOrMissionDesc>TO PARTNER WITH MARGINALIZED COMMUNITIES IN THE MOUNTAINS OF SOUTHERN HAITI TO ASSIST THEM IN DISCOVERING, CREATING, AND REALIZING THEIR OWN VISION OF SOCIOECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT FOR LASTING TRANSFORMATION.</ActivityOrMissionDesc>
      <VotingMembersGoverningBodyCnt>8</VotingMembersGoverningBodyCnt>
      <VotingMembersIndependentCnt>6</VotingMembersIndependentCnt>
      <TotalEmployeeCnt>5</TotalEmployeeCnt>
      <TotalVolunteersCnt>12</TotalVolunteersCnt>
      <TotalGrossUBIAmt>0</TotalGrossUBIAmt>
      <NetUnrelatedBusTxblIncmAmt>0</NetUnrelatedBusTxblIncmAmt>
      <PYContributionsGrantsAmt>802932</PYContributionsGrantsAmt>
      <CYContributionsGrantsAmt>459400</CYContributionsGrantsAmt>
      <PYProgramServiceRevenueAmt>0</PYProgramServiceRevenueAmt>
      <CYProgramServiceRevenueAmt>0</CYProgramServiceRevenueAmt>
      <PYInvestmentIncomeAmt>252</PYInvestmentIncomeAmt>
      <CYInvestmentIncomeAmt>6101</CYInvestmentIncomeAmt>
      <PYOtherRevenueAmt>-4616</PYOtherRevenueAmt>
      <CYOtherRevenueAmt>-10406</CYOtherRevenueAmt>
      <PYTotalRevenueAmt>798568</PYTotalRevenueAmt>
      <CYTotalRevenueAmt>455095</CYTotalRevenueAmt>
      <PYGrantsAndSimilarPaidAmt>0</PYGrantsAndSimilarPaidAmt>
      <CYGrantsAndSimilarPaidAmt>0</CYGrantsAndSimilarPaidAmt>
      <PYBenefitsPaidToMembersAmt>0</PYBenefitsPaidToMembersAmt>
      <CYBenefitsPaidToMembersAmt>0</CYBenefitsPaidToMembersAmt>
      <PYSalariesCompEmpBnftPaidAmt>180448</PYSalariesCompEmpBnftPaidAmt>
      <CYSalariesCompEmpBnftPaidAmt>235896</CYSalariesCompEmpBnftPaidAmt>
      <PYTotalProfFndrsngExpnsAmt>0</PYTotalProfFndrsngExpnsAmt>
      <CYTotalProfFndrsngExpnsAmt>0</CYTotalProfFndrsngExpnsAmt>
      <CYTotalFundraisingExpenseAmt>54425</CYTotalFundraisingExpenseAmt>
      <PYOtherExpensesAmt>465392</PYOtherExpensesAmt>
      <CYOtherExpensesAmt>288204</CYOtherExpensesAmt>
      <PYTotalExpensesAmt>645840</PYTotalExpensesAmt>
      <CYTotalExpensesAmt>524100</CYTotalExpensesAmt>
      <PYRevenuesLessExpensesAmt>152728</PYRevenuesLessExpensesAmt>
      <CYRevenuesLessExpensesAmt>-69005</CYRevenuesLessExpensesAmt>
      <TotalAssetsBOYAmt>573543</TotalAssetsBOYAmt>
      <TotalAssetsEOYAmt>508826</TotalAssetsEOYAmt>
      <TotalLiabilitiesBOYAmt>5528</TotalLiabilitiesBOYAmt>
      <TotalLiabilitiesEOYAmt>9817</TotalLiabilitiesEOYAmt>
      <NetAssetsOrFundBalancesBOYAmt>568015</NetAssetsOrFundBalancesBOYAmt>
      <NetAssetsOrFundBalancesEOYAmt>499009</NetAssetsOrFundBalancesEOYAmt>
      <InfoInScheduleOPartIIIInd>X</InfoInScheduleOPartIIIInd>
      <MissionDesc>COFHED'S MISSION IS TO PARTNER WITH MARGINALIZED COMMUNITIES IN THE MOUNTAINS OF SOUTHERN HAITI TO ASSIST THEM IN DISCOVERING, CREATING, AND REALIZING THEIR OWN VISION OF SOCIOECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT FOR LASTING TRANSFORMATION.</MissionDesc>
      <SignificantNewProgramSrvcInd>0</SignificantNewProgramSrvcInd>
      <SignificantChangeInd>0</SignificantChangeInd>
      <ExpenseAmt>382999</ExpenseAmt>
      <RevenueAmt>600</RevenueAmt>
      <Desc>COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT CATALYST TRAINING PROGRAMWE CELEBRATED A MAJOR MILESTONE IN OUR COMMUNITY FIELD ENGAGEMENT CATALYST TRAINING PROGRAM. OUR 18 TRAINEES GRADUATED ON AUGUST 20TH, 2022. IT WAS A GREAT CELEBRATION FOR OUR TRAINEES, OUR STAFF, BUT ALSO FOR THOSE IN ATTENDANCE. COMMUNITY MEMBERS FROM 10 PARTNER COMMUNITIES SHARED WITH THE AUDIENCE THEIR ENGAGEMENT EXPERIENCE WITH THE TRAINEES, LESSONS LEARNED IN COLLECTIVE CONVERSATIONS,AND TRANSFORMATION TAKING PLACE IN THEIR OWN LIVES AND COMMUNITIES. ATTENDEES TOOK TIME AFTER THE CEREMONY TO CONGRATULATE US AND TO ENCOURAGE US TO CONTINUE FORWARD WITH THE WORK. OVERALL WE CAN SAY IT WAS A GREAT AND EXCITED DAY FROM OUR TRAINEES, COMMUNITY MEMBERS AND OUR STAFF TO CELEBRATE TOGETHER.COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT CATALYST LEADER'S TRAINING PROGRAMWE STARTED OUR COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT CATALYST LEADER'S TRAINING ON FEBRUARY 4, 2023. WE WERE INUNDATED WITH APPLICATIONS WITHIN THE FIRST WEEK OF RECRUITMENT IN NOVEMBER 2022. WE HAVE A TOTAL OF 43 PARTICIPANTS (INCLUDING 3 OF OUR STAFF) ATTENDING CLASSES EVERY SATURDAY FROM 9:00 AM TO 1:30 PM THEY ARE FROM 14 COMMUNITIES ALL AROUND THE COMMUNE OF CAMPPERRIN. THE EDUCATION LEVELS OF PARTICIPANTS RANGE FROM HIGH SCHOOL TO UNIVERSITY, AND THE GROUP IS MADE UP OF EDUCATORS, TRADERS, HEALTH AGENTS, ELECTRICIANS, ACCOUNTANTS, FOREMAN MASONS, TILE SETTERS, MICROCREDIT AGENTS, COMMUNITY LEADERS, RELIGIOUS LEADERS, AND PASTORS.WE ARE COLLABORATING WITH SOME LOCAL EXPERTS TO OFFER TRAINING IN THEIR RELATED FIELD OF EXPERTISE. ONE OF THEM IS A PSYCHOLOGIST AND SHE PRESENTED A 3-DAY SEMINAR FOCUSING ON TRAUMA RELATED TO VARIOUS FORMS OF VIOLENCE, NATURAL DISASTERS, GRIEF AND DISCUSSED COPING SKILLS AND STRATEGIES FOR A HEALTHY RECOVERY. OUR SERVANT LEADERSHIP IN DEVELOPMENT WAS PRESENTED BY OUR COLLABORATOR AND FOUNDER OF UNIVERSIT SEED INTERNATIONAL INSTITUTE OF TROPICAL AGRICULTURE (USITA) OUR RIGHTS AND RESPONSIBILITIES/RURAL LAW /CIVIC ENGAGEMENT SEMINAR WAS PRESENTED BY A CIVIC AND CONSTITUTIONAL LAWYER.OUR 17 COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT CATALYSTS WHO GRADUATED ON AUGUST 20TH, 2022, ARE AT WORK ADVOCATING FOR THEIR COMMUNITIES AND ENGAGING AT A DEEPER LEVEL WITH FELLOW CITIZENS. COMMUNITY MEETINGS ARE HAPPENING EVERY WEEK AND MORE THAN EVER WE VALUE THEIR EFFORTS. WE ARE HOPEFUL WITH THEM, FOR THE SPACE THEY HAVE CREATED FOR THEMSELVES AND WITNESS HOW THESE SPACES BECOME SO VITAL TO SHARE IN THEIR GRIEF OVER THE COUNTRY, TO LEARN FROM EACH OTHER, TO PLAN, TO CONNECT SOCIALLY, EMOTIONALLY, AND SPIRITUALLY.ENGAGING WITH PARTNER COMMUNITIESWE ARE SO GRATEFUL THAT COMMUNITY MEMBERS AS THEY ARE ABLE TO GO BEYOND THE CRISES AFFECTING EVERY PART OF THE COUNTRY TO COME TOGETHER. JUSTIN ONE OF OUR GRADUATES FROM GUILLAUME HAD THIS TO SAY: "COMMUNITY MEMBERS ARE REALLY INTERESTED IN ATTENDING OUR COMMUNITY MEETINGS EVEN WHEN IT RAINS. THESE PAST FEW WEEKS, WE HARDLY HAVE ENOUGH ROOM IN OUR MEETING SPACE FOR EVERYONE; SOME PEOPLE HAVE TO STAND OUTSIDE BECAUSE OUR ROOM IS ALWAYS FULL. WE HAD LOTS OF RAIN IN SEPTEMBER AND DESPITE OF THAT WE HAD 4 MEETINGS AVERAGING 130 PEOPLE IN ATTENDANCE. THE ISSUES THE COMMUNITY IS FACING NOW IS HUNGER DUE TO HIGH PRICES OF FOOD. BUT I AM NOT DISCOURAGED AND THE COMMUNITY IS ON FIRE AND ALWAYS ASKING ABOUT WHAT OUR CONVERSATIONS WILL BE ABOUT. COMMUNITY MEMBERS ARE SO KEEN TO ATTEND OUR MEETINGS THAT I DON'T EVEN GIVE REMINDERS OF MEETING TIMES ANYMORE."FROM JANUARY-JUNE 2023 WE HAVE A TOTAL OF 178 COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT MEETINGS IN 10 COMMUNITIESAGROFORESTRY PROGRAMOUR AGRO-FORESTRY INITIATIVE, AIMS TO SUPPORT OUR PARTNER COMMUNITIES INCREASE THE DIVERSITY AND SUSTAINABILITY OF THEIR FARMING PRACTICES, AND ALSO CREATING REVENUE FOR US THROUGH FARMING. THIS INITIATIVE HAS BEEN SPEARHEADED BY OUR SPECIFIED STAFF AND OUR COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT CATALYSTS; SOME OF THEM HAVE EDUCATIONAL BACKGROUNDS IN AGRICULTURE. FONDATION COFHED HATI HAS ALREADY PLANTED THE FOLLOWING TREES: 223 PLANTAIN, 139 MORINGA, 199 CACAO, 40 SUCRIN (WILD INGA VERA) 206 PAPAYA, 60 CEDAR, 30 ACACIA, 37 COFFEE, AND 57 AVOCADO. TO ANOTHER PARCEL OF LAND, WE PLANTED 102 LBS. OF BEANS, 12LBS OF CORN, 440 MALANGA PLANTS, 312.5 KILOS OF YELLOW YAMS, 180 PINEAPPLE AND 50 CEDAR TREES.WE ARE SO EXCITED TO COLLABORATE WITH UNIVERSIT SEED INTERNATIONAL INSTITUTE OF TROPICAL AGRICULTURE (USITA) IN LES CAYES. WE HAVE AN AGROFORESTRY/VETERINARY STUDENT FROM USITA DOING AN INTERNSHIP WITH FONDATION COFHED HATI AND HE IS ALSO SUPPORTING SOME OF OUR PARTNER COMMUNITIES. HE WORKS IN OUR NURSERY AND OUR AGROFORESTRY GARDENS. HE OFFERS COMMUNITY TRAINING ON ANIMAL CARE, VEGETABLE PLANTING AND SOIL PRESERVATION. HE TRAINED OUR COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT CATALYSTS IN ANIMAL CARE AND TREATMENT. WE HAD HOPED FOR A GOOD HARVEST BUT EXTREME WEATHER CONDITIONS CAUSED MAJOR DAMAGE TO SOME OF OUR CROPS. FROM THE END OF 2022 UNTIL NOW, WE HAVE FACED VERY LONG PERIODS OF DROUGHT, WIND, AND HIGH TEMPERATURES; THUS, OUR PLANTS HAVE SUFFERED FROM SEVERE WATER STRESS. BUT WE'VE DEPLOYED A LOT OF EFFORTS WATERING OUR GARDENS LOCATED NEAR A WATER SOURCE. THESE EFFORTS ALLOWED US TO HARVEST SOME EGGPLANTS, CUCUMBERS, CABBAGE, PEPPERS, CARROTS, SPINACH, BEETS, OKRA AND BLACK BEANS. WE WERE ABLE TO SELL SOME. WE RECENTLY HARVESTED OUR CORN AND WE HAD A GOOD YIELD DESPITE THE HARSH CONDITIONS.AGROFORESTRY IN GUILLAUME COMMUNITYWE DISTRIBUTED TO GUILLAUME, AND VACHON COMMUNITIES:1731 SEEDLINGS OF CACAO298 CEDAR TREES50 INGA VERA WILD TREES15 ACACIA TREESON MAY 1ST, THE AGRICULTURAL DAY IN HAITI, PEOPLE FROM GUILLAUME AND ORGANISATION DES PAYSANS EN ACTION POUR L'EMANCIPATION DE CAMP-PERRIN (ORPAECC) PLANTED TREES AT THE TOP OF CAVAILLON RIVER TO REPAIR THE DAMAGE DONE BY THE EARTHQUAKE.90 MORINGA TREES216 PAPAYA TREES28 AVOCADO TREESCOMMUNITY-LED EDUCATION IMPACTIT HAS BEEN DIFFICULT FOR STUDENTS TO FINISH THEIR STUDIES IN THE PAST COUPLE YEARS. PARENTS, TEACHERS, AND STUDENTS FEEL THE CONTINUOUS STING OF FUEL CRISIS, ECONOMIC CRISIS, KIDNAPPINGS, CRIMES, PRICE HIKES AND UNAVAILABILITY OF BASIC GOODS. FAMILIES REGISTERED SEVERAL LOSSES BECAUSE OF THE OVERALL CRISIS IN THE COUNTRY. FOR INSTANCE, BECAUSE OF ROADBLOCKS, COMMUNITY PARENTS COULD NOT BRING THEIR GOODS TO PORTAU-PRINCE TO SELL AND BUY GOODS AT THE CAPITAL TO RESELL. THE IMPACT OF ALL THESE CHALLENGES WAS FELT BY BOTH JARDIN DES ROSSIGNOLS SCHOOL IN RAYMOND AND PETITE ACADMIE IN LOUGOU. IT HAS BEEN A STRUGGLE FOR PARENTS TO AFFORD THE EVER-INCREASING TUITION RATE. FOR INSTANCE, HIGH SCHOOL TUITION RANGES BETWEEN $200-390 USD PLUS BOOKS, UNIFORMS, AND LUNCH MONEY. FOR THE ACADEMIC YEAR OF 2022-2023, PETITE ACADMIE DE LOUGOU (PAL) OPENED ITS DOORS ON NOVEMBER 21ST, 2022, AND THEIR SCHOOL YEAR ENDED ON JULY 7TH, 2023. PAL SERVED STUDENTS FROM PRE-K TO 6TH GRADE. BOTH SPONSORED AND NON-SPONSORED STUDENTS RECEIVED THEIR REQUIRED BOOKS. PAL PROVIDED 36,085 HOT LUNCHES TO STUDENTS AND STAFF, AND PAID SALARIES TO 14 TEACHERS,1 PRINCIPAL, 3 CARETAKERS AND 1 JANITOR. THE STATE COVERS SALARIES FOR 6 STAFF.STUDENT PROFILE AT LA PETITE ACADMIE DE LOUGOUFOR THE ACADEMIC YEAR OF 2022-2023, JARDIN DES ROSSIGNOLS (JADRO) IN RAYMOND COMMUNITY OPENED ITS DOORS ON DECEMBER 5TH, 2022, AND THEIR SCHOOL YEAR ENDED ON JULY 10TH, 2023. JADRO SERVED STUDENTS FROM PRE-K TO 4TH GRADE, PAID SALARIES TO 7 TEACHERS, 1 PEDAGOGICAL ADVISOR 2 CARETAKERS, 3 KITCHEN STAFF AND 1 PRINCIPAL. THE SCHOOL PROVIDED 10,472 HEALTHY SNACKS AND 3,819 HOT LUNCHES TO STUDENTS AND STAFF.STUDENT PROFILE AT LE JARDIN DES ROSSIGNOLS DE RAYMONDWE ALSO SUPPORTED 54 HIGH SCHOOL AND 31 ELEMENTARY STUDENTS ATTENDING SCHOOL IN OTHER COMMUNITIES.COMMUNITY-LED ADVOCACY AND COLLABORATION FOR EDUCATIONONE OF OUR GOALS IN OUR COMMUNITY-LED ENGAGEMENT AND CATALYST IS TO SUPPORT THE CAPACITY OF COMMUNITY MEMBERS TO ACQUIRE MORE SKILLS AND DEVELOP THEIR AGENCY TO ADVOCATE FOR THEIR OWN CHANGES. THE COMMUNITY OF RAYMOND AND LOUGOU USED THEIR ADVOCACY SKILLS IN FINDING PARTNERS TO REBUILD THEIR SCHOOLS CRUMBLED BY THE AUGUST 14TH, 2021, EARTHQUAKE. WE ARE SO PROUD THAT THEY DID IT THEMSELVES. THE SCHOOL OF LOUGOU WAS BUILT BY UNICEF AND THEY HAVE 6 CLASSROOMS, A PRINCIPAL'S OFFICE, WATER FILTERS, SCHOOL DESKS, CHAIRS, AND A SANITARY BLOCK. LOUGOU SCHOOL USES ITS OWN SAVINGS TO BUILD A STORAGE ROOM. THE SCHOOL IN RAYMOND WASFUNDED BY CARITAS SWITZERLAND AND BUILT BY ASSOCIATION HATIENNE D'ASSISTANCE AGRICOLE, MDICALE, EDUCATIVE ET SOCIALE (AHAAMES). IT ALSO HAS SIX CLASSROOMS AND A SANITARY BLOCK.THE COMMUNITY OF RAYMOND COLLABORATED WITH KONBIT POU RANFSE AKSYON LOKAL (KORAL), A HAITIAN ORGANIZATION THAT SUPPLIED JADRO WITH MATERIALS AND EQUIPMENT FOR THEIR NEW SCHOOL. SOS CHILDREN'S VILLAGES IN HAITI PROVIDED EDUCATION FOR THE CHILDREN ON HOW TO MANAGE STRESS AND ANXIETY BROUGHT BY THE LAST EARTHQUAKE.</Desc>
      <TotalProgramServiceExpensesAmt>382999</TotalProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      <DescribedInSection501c3Ind referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1039100001">1</DescribedInSection501c3Ind>
      <ScheduleBRequiredInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1234500001">1</ScheduleBRequiredInd>
      <PoliticalCampaignActyInd>0</PoliticalCampaignActyInd>
      <LobbyingActivitiesInd>0</LobbyingActivitiesInd>
      <SubjectToProxyTaxInd>0</SubjectToProxyTaxInd>
      <DonorAdvisedFundInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</DonorAdvisedFundInd>
      <ConservationEasementsInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</ConservationEasementsInd>
      <CollectionsOfArtInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</CollectionsOfArtInd>
      <CreditCounselingInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</CreditCounselingInd>
      <DonorRstrOrQuasiEndowmentsInd>0</DonorRstrOrQuasiEndowmentsInd>
      <ReportLandBuildingEquipmentInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">1</ReportLandBuildingEquipmentInd>
      <ReportInvestmentsOtherSecInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</ReportInvestmentsOtherSecInd>
      <ReportProgramRelatedInvstInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</ReportProgramRelatedInvstInd>
      <ReportOtherAssetsInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</ReportOtherAssetsInd>
      <ReportOtherLiabilitiesInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</ReportOtherLiabilitiesInd>
      <IncludeFIN48FootnoteInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</IncludeFIN48FootnoteInd>
      <IndependentAuditFinclStmtInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</IndependentAuditFinclStmtInd>
      <ConsolidatedAuditFinclStmtInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</ConsolidatedAuditFinclStmtInd>
      <SchoolOperatingInd>0</SchoolOperatingInd>
      <ForeignOfficeInd>1</ForeignOfficeInd>
      <ForeignActivitiesInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040500001">1</ForeignActivitiesInd>
      <MoreThan5000KToOrgInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040500001">0</MoreThan5000KToOrgInd>
      <MoreThan5000KToIndividualsInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040500001">0</MoreThan5000KToIndividualsInd>
      <ProfessionalFundraisingInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1041300001">0</ProfessionalFundraisingInd>
      <FundraisingActivitiesInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1041300001">1</FundraisingActivitiesInd>
      <GamingActivitiesInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1041300001">0</GamingActivitiesInd>
      <OperateHospitalInd>0</OperateHospitalInd>
      <GrantsToOrganizationsInd>0</GrantsToOrganizationsInd>
      <GrantsToIndividualsInd>0</GrantsToIndividualsInd>
      <ScheduleJRequiredInd>0</ScheduleJRequiredInd>
      <TaxExemptBondsInd>0</TaxExemptBondsInd>
      <EngagedInExcessBenefitTransInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1042800001">0</EngagedInExcessBenefitTransInd>
      <PYExcessBenefitTransInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1042800001">0</PYExcessBenefitTransInd>
      <LoanOutstandingInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1042800001">0</LoanOutstandingInd>
      <GrantToRelatedPersonInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1042800001">0</GrantToRelatedPersonInd>
      <BusinessRlnWithOrgMemInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1042800001">0</BusinessRlnWithOrgMemInd>
      <BusinessRlnWithFamMemInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1042800001">1</BusinessRlnWithFamMemInd>
      <BusinessRlnWith35CtrlEntInd>0</BusinessRlnWith35CtrlEntInd>
      <DeductibleNonCashContriInd>0</DeductibleNonCashContriInd>
      <DeductibleArtContributionInd>0</DeductibleArtContributionInd>
      <TerminateOperationsInd>0</TerminateOperationsInd>
      <PartialLiquidationInd>0</PartialLiquidationInd>
      <DisregardedEntityInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1043400001">0</DisregardedEntityInd>
      <RelatedEntityInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1043400001">1</RelatedEntityInd>
      <RelatedOrganizationCtrlEntInd>0</RelatedOrganizationCtrlEntInd>
      <TrnsfrExmptNonChrtblRltdOrgInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1043400001">0</TrnsfrExmptNonChrtblRltdOrgInd>
      <ActivitiesConductedPrtshpInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1043400001">0</ActivitiesConductedPrtshpInd>
      <ScheduleORequiredInd>1</ScheduleORequiredInd>
      <IRPDocumentCnt>3</IRPDocumentCnt>
      <IRPDocumentW2GCnt>0</IRPDocumentW2GCnt>
      <BackupWthldComplianceInd>1</BackupWthldComplianceInd>
      <EmployeeCnt>5</EmployeeCnt>
      <EmploymentTaxReturnsFiledInd>1</EmploymentTaxReturnsFiledInd>
      <UnrelatedBusIncmOverLimitInd>0</UnrelatedBusIncmOverLimitInd>
      <ForeignFinancialAccountInd>1</ForeignFinancialAccountInd>
      <ForeignCountryCd>HA</ForeignCountryCd>
      <ProhibitedTaxShelterTransInd>0</ProhibitedTaxShelterTransInd>
      <TaxablePartyNotificationInd>0</TaxablePartyNotificationInd>
      <NondeductibleContributionsInd>0</NondeductibleContributionsInd>
      <QuidProQuoContributionsInd>1</QuidProQuoContributionsInd>
      <QuidProQuoContriDisclInd>1</QuidProQuoContriDisclInd>
      <Form8282PropertyDisposedOfInd>0</Form8282PropertyDisposedOfInd>
      <RcvFndsToPayPrsnlBnftCntrctInd>0</RcvFndsToPayPrsnlBnftCntrctInd>
      <PayPremiumsPrsnlBnftCntrctInd>0</PayPremiumsPrsnlBnftCntrctInd>
      <IndoorTanningServicesInd>0</IndoorTanningServicesInd>
      <SubjToTaxRmnrtnExPrchtPymtInd>0</SubjToTaxRmnrtnExPrchtPymtInd>
      <SubjectToExcsTaxNetInvstIncInd>0</SubjectToExcsTaxNetInvstIncInd>
      <InfoInScheduleOPartVIInd>X</InfoInScheduleOPartVIInd>
      <GoverningBodyVotingMembersCnt>8</GoverningBodyVotingMembersCnt>
      <IndependentVotingMemberCnt>6</IndependentVotingMemberCnt>
      <FamilyOrBusinessRlnInd>1</FamilyOrBusinessRlnInd>
      <DelegationOfMgmtDutiesInd>0</DelegationOfMgmtDutiesInd>
      <ChangeToOrgDocumentsInd>0</ChangeToOrgDocumentsInd>
      <MaterialDiversionOrMisuseInd>0</MaterialDiversionOrMisuseInd>
      <MembersOrStockholdersInd>0</MembersOrStockholdersInd>
      <ElectionOfBoardMembersInd>0</ElectionOfBoardMembersInd>
      <DecisionsSubjectToApprovaInd>0</DecisionsSubjectToApprovaInd>
      <MinutesOfGoverningBodyInd>1</MinutesOfGoverningBodyInd>
      <MinutesOfCommitteesInd>1</MinutesOfCommitteesInd>
      <OfficerMailingAddressInd>0</OfficerMailingAddressInd>
      <LocalChaptersInd>0</LocalChaptersInd>
      <Form990ProvidedToGvrnBodyInd>1</Form990ProvidedToGvrnBodyInd>
      <ConflictOfInterestPolicyInd>1</ConflictOfInterestPolicyInd>
      <AnnualDisclosureCoveredPrsnInd>1</AnnualDisclosureCoveredPrsnInd>
      <RegularMonitoringEnfrcInd>1</RegularMonitoringEnfrcInd>
      <WhistleblowerPolicyInd>0</WhistleblowerPolicyInd>
      <DocumentRetentionPolicyInd>0</DocumentRetentionPolicyInd>
      <CompensationProcessCEOInd>1</CompensationProcessCEOInd>
      <CompensationProcessOtherInd>1</CompensationProcessOtherInd>
      <InvestmentInJointVentureInd>0</InvestmentInJointVentureInd>
      <StatesWhereCopyOfReturnIsFldCd>MN</StatesWhereCopyOfReturnIsFldCd>
      <UponRequestInd>X</UponRequestInd>
      <BooksInCareOfDetail>
        <BusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>NICAISE AVIGNON</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </BusinessName>
        <PhoneNum>6517056247</PhoneNum>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>PO BOX 4094</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>SAINT PAUL</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>MN</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>551040094</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
      </BooksInCareOfDetail>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>NICAISE AVIGNON</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>40.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <OfficerInd>X</OfficerInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>45660</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>2010</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>HARRY SAINT PREUX</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>BOARD CHAIR</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>6.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <OfficerInd>X</OfficerInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>ANNA MARIE LIVELY</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>SECRETARY</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>6.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <OfficerInd>X</OfficerInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>JERRY FENNER</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>TREASURER</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>15.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <OfficerInd>X</OfficerInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>MATT AVIGNON-PETERSEN</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>DIRECTOR</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>10.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>ALLI PHILLIPS</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>DIRECTOR</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>5.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>GLENN SMUCKER</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>DIRECTOR</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>5.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>JULIE SCOTT</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>DIRECTOR</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>2.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <TotalReportableCompFromOrgAmt>45660</TotalReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
      <TotReportableCompRltdOrgAmt>0</TotReportableCompRltdOrgAmt>
      <TotalOtherCompensationAmt>2010</TotalOtherCompensationAmt>
      <IndivRcvdGreaterThan100KCnt>0</IndivRcvdGreaterThan100KCnt>
      <FormerOfcrEmployeesListedInd>0</FormerOfcrEmployeesListedInd>
      <TotalCompGreaterThan150KInd>0</TotalCompGreaterThan150KInd>
      <CompensationFromOtherSrcsInd>0</CompensationFromOtherSrcsInd>
      <CntrctRcvdGreaterThan100KCnt>0</CntrctRcvdGreaterThan100KCnt>
      <FundraisingAmt>45793</FundraisingAmt>
      <AllOtherContributionsAmt>413607</AllOtherContributionsAmt>
      <NoncashContributionsAmt>3755</NoncashContributionsAmt>
      <TotalContributionsAmt>459400</TotalContributionsAmt>
      <InvestmentIncomeGrp>
        <TotalRevenueColumnAmt>4269</TotalRevenueColumnAmt>
        <ExclusionAmt>4269</ExclusionAmt>
      </InvestmentIncomeGrp>
      <GrossAmountSalesAssetsGrp>
        <SecuritiesAmt>1832</SecuritiesAmt>
      </GrossAmountSalesAssetsGrp>
      <LessCostOthBasisSalesExpnssGrp>
        <SecuritiesAmt>0</SecuritiesAmt>
      </LessCostOthBasisSalesExpnssGrp>
      <GainOrLossGrp>
        <SecuritiesAmt>1832</SecuritiesAmt>
      </GainOrLossGrp>
      <NetGainOrLossInvestmentsGrp>
        <TotalRevenueColumnAmt>1832</TotalRevenueColumnAmt>
        <ExclusionAmt>1832</ExclusionAmt>
      </NetGainOrLossInvestmentsGrp>
      <FundraisingGrossIncomeAmt>16595</FundraisingGrossIncomeAmt>
      <ContriRptFundraisingEventAmt>45793</ContriRptFundraisingEventAmt>
      <FundraisingDirectExpensesAmt>27601</FundraisingDirectExpensesAmt>
      <NetIncmFromFundraisingEvtGrp>
        <TotalRevenueColumnAmt>-11006</TotalRevenueColumnAmt>
        <ExclusionAmt>-11006</ExclusionAmt>
      </NetIncmFromFundraisingEvtGrp>
      <OtherRevenueMiscGrp>
        <Desc>MISCELLANEOUS</Desc>
        <BusinessCd>900099</BusinessCd>
        <TotalRevenueColumnAmt>600</TotalRevenueColumnAmt>
        <RelatedOrExemptFuncIncomeAmt>600</RelatedOrExemptFuncIncomeAmt>
      </OtherRevenueMiscGrp>
      <OtherRevenueTotalAmt>600</OtherRevenueTotalAmt>
      <TotalRevenueGrp>
        <TotalRevenueColumnAmt>455095</TotalRevenueColumnAmt>
        <RelatedOrExemptFuncIncomeAmt>600</RelatedOrExemptFuncIncomeAmt>
        <UnrelatedBusinessRevenueAmt>0</UnrelatedBusinessRevenueAmt>
        <ExclusionAmt>-4905</ExclusionAmt>
      </TotalRevenueGrp>
      <InfoInScheduleOPartIXInd>X</InfoInScheduleOPartIXInd>
      <CompCurrentOfcrDirectorsGrp>
        <TotalAmt>50041</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>32903</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>7786</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
        <FundraisingAmt>9352</FundraisingAmt>
      </CompCurrentOfcrDirectorsGrp>
      <OtherSalariesAndWagesGrp>
        <TotalAmt>154981</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>101624</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>24283</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
        <FundraisingAmt>29074</FundraisingAmt>
      </OtherSalariesAndWagesGrp>
      <OtherEmployeeBenefitsGrp>
        <TotalAmt>11322</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>7925</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>1472</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
        <FundraisingAmt>1925</FundraisingAmt>
      </OtherEmployeeBenefitsGrp>
      <PayrollTaxesGrp>
        <TotalAmt>19552</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>14211</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>1923</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
        <FundraisingAmt>3418</FundraisingAmt>
      </PayrollTaxesGrp>
      <FeesForServicesAccountingGrp>
        <TotalAmt>15459</TotalAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>15459</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </FeesForServicesAccountingGrp>
      <FeesForServicesOtherGrp>
        <TotalAmt>24523</TotalAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>24523</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </FeesForServicesOtherGrp>
      <TravelGrp>
        <TotalAmt>2575</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>885</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>291</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
        <FundraisingAmt>1399</FundraisingAmt>
      </TravelGrp>
      <DepreciationDepletionGrp>
        <TotalAmt>3358</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>3358</ProgramServicesAmt>
      </DepreciationDepletionGrp>
      <InsuranceGrp>
        <TotalAmt>1105</TotalAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>1105</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </InsuranceGrp>
      <OtherExpensesGrp>
        <Desc>EDUCATION</Desc>
        <TotalAmt>57001</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>57001</ProgramServicesAmt>
      </OtherExpensesGrp>
      <OtherExpensesGrp>
        <Desc>ECONOMIC SUSTAINABILITY</Desc>
        <TotalAmt>50199</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>50199</ProgramServicesAmt>
      </OtherExpensesGrp>
      <OtherExpensesGrp>
        <Desc>COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT CE</Desc>
        <TotalAmt>37910</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>37910</ProgramServicesAmt>
      </OtherExpensesGrp>
      <OtherExpensesGrp>
        <Desc>SPECIAL PROGRAMS</Desc>
        <TotalAmt>27323</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>27323</ProgramServicesAmt>
      </OtherExpensesGrp>
      <AllOtherExpensesGrp>
        <TotalAmt>68751</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>49660</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>9834</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
        <FundraisingAmt>9257</FundraisingAmt>
      </AllOtherExpensesGrp>
      <TotalFunctionalExpensesGrp>
        <TotalAmt>524100</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>382999</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>86676</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
        <FundraisingAmt>54425</FundraisingAmt>
      </TotalFunctionalExpensesGrp>
      <CashNonInterestBearingGrp>
        <BOYAmt>26933</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>10571</EOYAmt>
      </CashNonInterestBearingGrp>
      <SavingsAndTempCashInvstGrp>
        <BOYAmt>282300</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>326401</EOYAmt>
      </SavingsAndTempCashInvstGrp>
      <PledgesAndGrantsReceivableGrp>
        <BOYAmt>140600</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>50000</EOYAmt>
      </PledgesAndGrantsReceivableGrp>
      <AccountsReceivableGrp>
        <EOYAmt>2117</EOYAmt>
      </AccountsReceivableGrp>
      <PrepaidExpensesDefrdChargesGrp>
        <BOYAmt>4467</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>3852</EOYAmt>
      </PrepaidExpensesDefrdChargesGrp>
      <LandBldgEquipCostOrOtherBssAmt>234822</LandBldgEquipCostOrOtherBssAmt>
      <LandBldgEquipAccumDeprecAmt>118937</LandBldgEquipAccumDeprecAmt>
      <LandBldgEquipBasisNetGrp>
        <BOYAmt>119243</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>115885</EOYAmt>
      </LandBldgEquipBasisNetGrp>
      <TotalAssetsGrp>
        <BOYAmt>573543</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>508826</EOYAmt>
      </TotalAssetsGrp>
      <AccountsPayableAccrExpnssGrp>
        <BOYAmt>5528</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>9817</EOYAmt>
      </AccountsPayableAccrExpnssGrp>
      <TotalLiabilitiesGrp>
        <BOYAmt>5528</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>9817</EOYAmt>
      </TotalLiabilitiesGrp>
      <OrganizationFollowsFASB117Ind>X</OrganizationFollowsFASB117Ind>
      <NoDonorRestrictionNetAssetsGrp>
        <BOYAmt>376006</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>389713</EOYAmt>
      </NoDonorRestrictionNetAssetsGrp>
      <DonorRestrictionNetAssetsGrp>
        <BOYAmt>192009</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>109296</EOYAmt>
      </DonorRestrictionNetAssetsGrp>
      <TotalNetAssetsFundBalanceGrp>
        <BOYAmt>568015</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>499009</EOYAmt>
      </TotalNetAssetsFundBalanceGrp>
      <TotLiabNetAssetsFundBalanceGrp>
        <BOYAmt>573543</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>508826</EOYAmt>
      </TotLiabNetAssetsFundBalanceGrp>
      <ReconcilationRevenueExpnssAmt>-69005</ReconcilationRevenueExpnssAmt>
      <PriorPeriodAdjustmentsAmt>-1</PriorPeriodAdjustmentsAmt>
      <OtherChangesInNetAssetsAmt>0</OtherChangesInNetAssetsAmt>
      <MethodOfAccountingAccrualInd>X</MethodOfAccountingAccrualInd>
      <AccountantCompileOrReviewInd>0</AccountantCompileOrReviewInd>
      <FSAuditedInd>0</FSAuditedInd>
      <FederalGrantAuditRequiredInd>0</FederalGrantAuditRequiredInd>
    </IRS990>
    <IRS990ScheduleA documentId="RetDoc1039100001">
      <PublicOrganization170Ind>X</PublicOrganization170Ind>
      <GiftsGrantsContriRcvd170Grp>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>366396</CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>261191</CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>609631</CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>802932</CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearAmt>459400</CurrentTaxYearAmt>
        <TotalAmt>2499550</TotalAmt>
      </GiftsGrantsContriRcvd170Grp>
      <TotalCalendarYear170Grp>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>366396</CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>261191</CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>609631</CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>802932</CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearAmt>459400</CurrentTaxYearAmt>
        <TotalAmt>2499550</TotalAmt>
      </TotalCalendarYear170Grp>
      <SubstantialContributorsTotAmt>928226</SubstantialContributorsTotAmt>
      <PublicSupportTotal170Amt>1571324</PublicSupportTotal170Amt>
      <GrossInvestmentIncome170Grp>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>11</CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>7</CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>103</CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>252</CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearAmt>4269</CurrentTaxYearAmt>
        <TotalAmt>4642</TotalAmt>
      </GrossInvestmentIncome170Grp>
      <OtherIncome170Grp>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>250</CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>1932</CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearAmt>17195</CurrentTaxYearAmt>
        <TotalAmt>19377</TotalAmt>
      </OtherIncome170Grp>
      <TotalSupportAmt>2523569</TotalSupportAmt>
      <PublicSupportCY170Pct>0.62270</PublicSupportCY170Pct>
      <PublicSupportPY170Pct>0.66930</PublicSupportPY170Pct>
      <ThirtyThrPctSuprtTestsCY170Ind>X</ThirtyThrPctSuprtTestsCY170Ind>
      <Form990ScheduleAPartVIGrp>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>SCHEDULE A, PART II, LINE 10, EXPLANATION OF OTHER INCOME:</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>MISCELLANEOUS - 2020 AMOUNT: $ 250. 2021 AMOUNT: $ 700. 2022 AMOUNT: $ 600. FUNDRAISING INCOME - 2021 AMOUNT: $ 1,232. 2022 AMOUNT: $ 16,595.</ExplanationTxt>
      </Form990ScheduleAPartVIGrp>
    </IRS990ScheduleA>
    <IRS990ScheduleB documentId="RetDoc1234500001">
      <ContributorInformationGrp>
        <ContributorNum>RESTRICTED</ContributorNum>
        <ContributorBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1>RESTRICTED</BusinessNameLine1>
        </ContributorBusinessName>
        <ContributorUSAddress>
          <AddressLine1>RESTRICTED</AddressLine1>
          <AddressLine2>RESTRICTED</AddressLine2>
          <City>RESTRICTED</City>
          <State>RESTRICTED</State>
          <ZIPCode>RESTRICTED</ZIPCode>
        </ContributorUSAddress>
        <TotalContributionsAmt>RESTRICTED</TotalContributionsAmt>
      </ContributorInformationGrp>
    </IRS990ScheduleB>
    <IRS990ScheduleD documentId="RetDoc1040000001">
      <BuildingsGrp>
        <OtherCostOrOtherBasisAmt>134539</OtherCostOrOtherBasisAmt>
        <DepreciationAmt>18654</DepreciationAmt>
        <BookValueAmt>115885</BookValueAmt>
      </BuildingsGrp>
      <LeaseholdImprovementsGrp>
        <OtherCostOrOtherBasisAmt>928</OtherCostOrOtherBasisAmt>
        <DepreciationAmt>928</DepreciationAmt>
        <BookValueAmt>0</BookValueAmt>
      </LeaseholdImprovementsGrp>
      <EquipmentGrp>
        <OtherCostOrOtherBasisAmt>99355</OtherCostOrOtherBasisAmt>
        <DepreciationAmt>99355</DepreciationAmt>
        <BookValueAmt>0</BookValueAmt>
      </EquipmentGrp>
      <TotalBookValueLandBuildingsAmt>115885</TotalBookValueLandBuildingsAmt>
      <FootnoteTextInd>X</FootnoteTextInd>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>PART X, LINE 2:</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>THE ORGANIZATION IS EXEMPT FROM FEDERAL AND STATE INCOME TAXES UNDER SECTION 501(C)(3) OF THE INTERNAL REVENUE CODE, THEREFORE, THE STATEMENTS DO NOT INCLUDE A PROVISION FOR INCOME TAXES, BUT THE ORGANIZATION IS SUBJECT TO INCOME TAXES ON NET UNRELATED BUSINESS INCOME. THE ORGANIZATION REVIEWS INCOME TAX POSITIONS TAKEN OR EXPECTED TO BE TAKEN IN INCOME TAX RETURNS TO DETERMINE IF THERE ARE ANY INCOME TAX UNCERTAINTIES. THIS INCLUDES POSITIONS THAT THE ENTITY IS EXEMPT FROM INCOME TAXES OR NOT SUBJECT TO INCOME TAXES ON UNRELATED BUSINESS INCOME. THE ORGANIZATION RECOGNIZES TAX BENEFITS FROM UNCERTAIN TAX POSITIONS ONLY IF IT IS MORE LIKELY THAN NOT THAT THE TAX POSITIONS WILL BE SUSTAINED ON EXAMINATION BY TAXING AUTHORITIES, BASED ON THE TECHNICAL MERITS OF THE POSITIONS. THE ORGANIZATION HAS IDENTIFIED NO INCOME TAX UNCERTAINTIES.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
    </IRS990ScheduleD>
    <IRS990ScheduleF documentId="RetDoc1040500001">
      <GrantRecordsMaintainedInd>1</GrantRecordsMaintainedInd>
      <AccountActivitiesOutsideUSGrp>
        <RegionTxt>ACTIVITIES IN HAITI</RegionTxt>
        <OfficesCnt>1</OfficesCnt>
        <EmployeeCnt>13</EmployeeCnt>
        <TypeOfActivitiesConductedTxt>PROGRAM SERVICES</TypeOfActivitiesConductedTxt>
        <SpecificServicesProvidedTxt>OFFICE SUPPORT AND PROJECTS BENEFITING INDIVIDUAL AND VARIOUS PARTNER COMMUNITIES</SpecificServicesProvidedTxt>
        <RegionTotalExpendituresAmt>273307</RegionTotalExpendituresAmt>
      </AccountActivitiesOutsideUSGrp>
      <SubtotalOfficesCnt>1</SubtotalOfficesCnt>
      <SubtotalEmployeesCnt>13</SubtotalEmployeesCnt>
      <ContinuationTotalOfficeCnt>0</ContinuationTotalOfficeCnt>
      <ContinuationTotalEmployeeCnt>0</ContinuationTotalEmployeeCnt>
      <TotalOfficeCnt>1</TotalOfficeCnt>
      <TotalEmployeeCnt>13</TotalEmployeeCnt>
      <SubtotalSpentAmt>273307</SubtotalSpentAmt>
      <ContinuationSpentAmt>0</ContinuationSpentAmt>
      <TotalSpentAmt>273307</TotalSpentAmt>
      <TransferToForeignCorpInd>0</TransferToForeignCorpInd>
      <InterestInForeignTrustInd>0</InterestInForeignTrustInd>
      <ForeignCorpOwnershipInd>0</ForeignCorpOwnershipInd>
      <PassiveForeignInvestmestCoInd>0</PassiveForeignInvestmestCoInd>
      <ForeignPartnershipInd>0</ForeignPartnershipInd>
      <BoycottCountriesInd>0</BoycottCountriesInd>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>PART III ACCOUNTING METHOD:</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>PART I, LINE 2</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>GRANTS OBTAINED DURING FY 2022-23 ARE SENT BY WIRE TRANFERS TO THE BANK ACCOUNT OF COFHED IN MN. IN SOME CASES, A SIGNED CONFIRMATION OF FUNDS RECEIVED IS SENT TO THE GRANTOR FOR EACH GRANT RECEIVED. TO SEND GRANT FUNDS TO HAITI, DISBURSEMENT REQUESTS ARE PREPARED BY THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR AND SENT TO THE TREASURER. FUNDS EXPENDITURES ARE TRACKED IN EXCEL FILES, AND REQUESTED REPORTS PRODUCED (BOTH NARRATIVE AND FINANCIAL) ARE SENT TO BOTH THE GRANTORS AND COFHED TREASURER.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
    </IRS990ScheduleF>
    <IRS990ScheduleG documentId="RetDoc1041300001">
      <FundraisingEventInformationGrp>
        <Event1Nm>GALA</Event1Nm>
        <GrossReceiptsEvent1Amt>62388</GrossReceiptsEvent1Amt>
        <CharitableContriEvent1Amt>45793</CharitableContriEvent1Amt>
        <GrossRevenueEvent1Amt>16595</GrossRevenueEvent1Amt>
        <RentFacilityCostsEvent1Amt>18543</RentFacilityCostsEvent1Amt>
        <EntertainmentEvent1Amt>1345</EntertainmentEvent1Amt>
        <OtherDirectExpensesEvent1Amt>7713</OtherDirectExpensesEvent1Amt>
        <GrossReceiptsTotalAmt>62388</GrossReceiptsTotalAmt>
        <CharitableContributionsTotAmt>45793</CharitableContributionsTotAmt>
        <GrossRevenueTotalEventsAmt>16595</GrossRevenueTotalEventsAmt>
        <RentFcltyCostsTotalEventsAmt>18543</RentFcltyCostsTotalEventsAmt>
        <EntertainmentTotalEventsAmt>1345</EntertainmentTotalEventsAmt>
        <OthDirectExpnssTotalEventsAmt>7713</OthDirectExpnssTotalEventsAmt>
        <DirectExpenseSummaryEventsAmt>27601</DirectExpenseSummaryEventsAmt>
        <NetIncomeSummaryAmt>-11006</NetIncomeSummaryAmt>
      </FundraisingEventInformationGrp>
    </IRS990ScheduleG>
    <IRS990ScheduleL documentId="RetDoc1042800001">
      <BusTrInvolveInterestedPrsnGrp>
        <NameOfInterested>
          <PersonNm>MADELEINE AVIGNON</PersonNm>
        </NameOfInterested>
        <RelationshipDescriptionTxt>SPOUSE OF EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR</RelationshipDescriptionTxt>
        <TransactionAmt>59353</TransactionAmt>
        <TransactionDesc>EMPLOYMENT WAGES</TransactionDesc>
        <SharingOfRevenuesInd>0</SharingOfRevenuesInd>
      </BusTrInvolveInterestedPrsnGrp>
      <BusTrInvolveInterestedPrsnGrp>
        <NameOfInterested>
          <PersonNm>NORKA AVIGNON PETERSEN</PersonNm>
        </NameOfInterested>
        <RelationshipDescriptionTxt>CHILD OF EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR</RelationshipDescriptionTxt>
        <TransactionAmt>22880</TransactionAmt>
        <TransactionDesc>EMPLOYMENT WAGES</TransactionDesc>
        <SharingOfRevenuesInd>0</SharingOfRevenuesInd>
      </BusTrInvolveInterestedPrsnGrp>
    </IRS990ScheduleL>
    <IRS990ScheduleO documentId="RetDoc1044400001">
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>FORM 990, PART III, LINE 4A</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>EMERGING LEADERS CAPACITY BUILDING WE ARE SO PROUD AND HAPPY THAT 5 NURSING STUDENTS FROM OUR PARTNER COMMUNITIES GRADUATED AFTER 4 YEARS OF STUDIES. WE COLLABORATED WITH CHRISTIAN INSTITUTE FOR TECHNICAL STUDIES (C-TECH), A BRANCH OF FOUNDATION FOR THE CHILDREN OF HAITI (FEH), A HAITIAN-LED INSTITUTION WHO PROVIDED PARTIAL SCHOLARSHIP TO THE STUDENTS. THE SCHOOL IS LOCATED IN MUSSOTE IN THE NIPPES DEPARTMENT. BUILDING THE CAPACITY OF EMERGENT LEADERS DURING THE FISCAL YEAR 2022-2023 IN THE FOLLOWING SUBJECT AREAS OF STUDY 6 GRADUATED FROM NURSING 2 IN CIVIL ENGINEERING 6 CURRENTLY STUDYING NURSING 1 IN LAW SCHOOL 1 IN COMPUTER TECHNOLOGY 2 IN ADMINISTRATIVE SCIENCES 4 IN CLOTHING CONSTRUCTION &amp; DESIGN 1 IN AUTO MECHANIC 1 IN HOME ECONOMICS 1 IN AGRONOMY 1 IN BANKING COMMUNITY HEALTH IMPACT MOST HEALTH SERVICES ARE PROVIDED IN COMMUNITIES OF LOUGOU AND RAYMOND. 419 CHILDREN HAD WELL CHILD CHECKUPS (RAYMOND AND LOUGOU) 145 CHILDREN RECEIVED DEWORMING TREATMENT 8 CHILDREN WERE TREATED FOR MALNUTRITION IN RAYMOND 160 CHILDREN RECEIVED VITAMIN A IN RAYMOND COMMUNITY 628 ADULTS WERE SEEN AT THE CLINIC IN LOUGOU 300 WOMEN RECEIVED FAMILY PLANNING SERVICES AT THE CLINIC 8 WOMEN GAVE BIRTH TO 8 HEALTHY NEWBORNS IN LOUGOU 174 HOME HEALTH VISITS IN 6 COMMUNITIES. PATIENTS RECEIVED MEDICATIONS AND HEALTH EDUCATION . MOST PATIENTS SEEN SUFFER FROM HYPERTENSION, DIABETES, SKIN IRRITATIONS, COMMON COLD, VAGINAL INFECTIONS, EYE INFECTIONS, MALNUTRITION. COMMUNITY HEALTH &amp; PREVENTION CAMPAIGN TOOK PLACE IN THE LAST QUARTER OF THE YEAR IN GARATTE, BALIZ, DUVEZIN, GUILLAUME, ACQUIER AND RAYMOND. COMMUNITY WOMEN-LED MICROCREDIT MICROCREDIT ORGANIZATION OF ACTIVE WOMEN FOR THE DEVELOPMENT OF LOUGOU (MOFADEL) IS A FEMALE LED MICROLENDING ENTERPRISE IN LOUGOU COMMUNITY. AFTER THE DEVASTATING EARTHQUAKE IN 2022, THEY STARTED TO OFFER AGRO LOANS TO FAMILIES INCLUDING 48 WOMEN FARMERS TO REPLACE LOST CROPS AND SUPPORT FAMILIES ECONOMICALLY WHICH HAS LED TO INCREASED INTEREST IN MOFADEL AS MORE AND MORE PEOPLE FROM SURROUNDING RURAL COMMUNITIES ARE SEEKING MEMBERSHIP. DESPITE REGISTERING TWO SEASONS OF DROUGHTS, 71% OF THE BORROWERS HAVE REPAID THEIR LOANS FULLY WHILE 29% ARE IN THE PROCESS OF REPAYMENTS. MOFADEL MEMBERSHIP HAS INCREASED TO 493 MEMBERS (274 WOMEN,188 MEN AND 31 COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS). TEN YEARS AGO, INDIVIDUAL LOANS STARTED AT $35.00 USD, NOW QUALIFIED BORROWERS ARE GETTING LOANS UP TO $1,500.00 USD. MOFADEL REPRESENTS A PILLAR OF HOPE AND CHANGE NOT ONLY FOR LOUGOU BUT FOR EIGHT SURROUNDING NEIGHBORHOOD COMMUNITIES. THE AGRICULTURAL LOAN PROGRAM WITHIN MOFADEL PROVIDES LOANS TO FAMILIES ENGAGED IN AGRICULTURAL ACTIVITIES SUCH AS THE PURCHASING OF SEEDS, SEEDLINGS, AND OTHER RESOURCES. THE LOAN TERM IS FROM 6 TO 12 MONTHS. LIVESTOCK REPLACEMENT ANIMAL HUSBANDRY IS AN ACTIVITY THAT PEOPLE IN THE COMMUNITY ARE INTERESTED IN BECAUSE THEY UNDERSTAND THAT ANIMAL HUSBANDRY CAN HELP THEM PAY FOR THEIR CHILDREN'S SCHOOLING. ALSO IS A WAY TO STRENGTHEN THE LOCAL ECONOMY. ALTHOUGH GOAT/SHEEP BREEDERS COMPLAIN A LOT ABOUT DOGS KILLING AND EATING THEIR ANIMALS WHEN THEY ARE LEFT TO SLEEP IN PASTURES. COMMUNITY LEADERS ENCOURAGE BENEFICIARIES TO STOP LETTING THEIR ANIMALS SLEEP ON GRAZING LAND BUT TO BRING THEM BACK HOME SO THAT THE ANIMALS CAN BE MORE SECURE. COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT CATALYSTS TRAIN COMMUNITY MEMBERS IN ALL ASPECTS OF ANIMAL CARE AND WELFARE. TO KEEP GROWING THIS PROGRAM COMMUNITY MEMBERS AGREE TO PASS ON THE GIFT IS IMPLEMENTED. THIS MEANS BENEFICIARIES HAVE TO PASS ONE OF THEIR NEWBORNS TO ANOTHER FAMILY. BREEDING ANIMALS REPRESENTS HOPE FOR FAMILIES. FOR THE MOST VULNERABLE FAMILIES IN OUR COMMUNITY PARTNERS, OWNING A COW, A GOAT, A SHEEP, A COW, A PAIR OF RABBITS, IS AN IMPORTANT RESOURCE. THERE IS A PROVERB THAT SAYS "ANIMALS ARE THE PEASANT'S BANK CARD" BECAUSE THEY CAN SELL THAT ANIMAL OR USE IT IN DIFFICULT TIMES. WE DISTRIBUTED 535 GOATS AND SHEEP, 11 COWS, AND 10 RABBITS TO FAMILIES IN OUR PARTNER COMMUNITIES COMMUNITY HOUSING AND SANITATION ONE OF THE DETERMINANTS OF HEALTH IS IMPROVED SANITATION IN ONE'S IMMEDIATE ENVIRONMENT. MAINTAINING A HEALTHY ENVIRONMENT IS ALSO ONE OF THE PARTNER COMMUNITIES' PRIORITIES. WE HAD HOPE TO SUPPORT 2 COMMUNITIES WITH 10 LATRINES THIS YEAR, BUT THEY COULD ONLY BUILD 7 LATRINES BECAUSE OF SKYROCKETED PRICES OF CONSTRUCTION MATERIALS DUE TO INFLATION. FAMILIES ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE ROOF AND THE DOOR MATERIALS. MANY FAMILIES ARE WILLING TO ACCOMMODATE THEIR NEIGHBORS IN TIMES OF NEED. IN COLLABORATION WITH FONDATION POUR LES ENFANTS D'HATI (FEH), JACQUES, A TRAINED ENGINEER FROM LOUGOU COMMUNITY HAS BEEN WORKING ON BUILDING HOUSING UNITS FOR 5 RECENTLY GRADUATED NURSING STUDENTS FROM LOUGOU, PICOT, AND GUILLAUME WHOSE HOMES WERE DESTROYED IN THE AUGUST 14TH, 2021 EARTHQUAKE. YOUTH CLUB IN LOUGOU AND RAYMOND THE PURPOSE OF THE YOUTH CLUB IS TO RAISE AWARENESS OF THE NECESSITY FOR TAKING STEPS TO ENGAGE YOUTHS IN CONVERSATIONS ABOUT THE ISSUE OF VIOLENCE AGAINST GIRLS IN COMMUNITY PARTNERS. ENGAGING BOYS TO BECOME GIRLS' ALLIES AND ADDRESSING NORMS AND VALUES THAT PERPETRATE VIOLENCE AGAINST GIRLS. COMMUNITY LEADERS AND STAFF SUPPORTED THE YOUTH CLUBS IN MANY ACTIVITIES 3 DAYS A WEEK IN THE SUMMER AND ON SATURDAYS DURING SCHOOL DAYS. KIDS AND YOUNG PEOPLE LEARNED CRAFTS, PLAYED, PARTICIPATED IN BIBLE STUDIES, AND DISCUSSIONS ON VARIOUS ISSUES RELATED TO VIOLENCE ON GIRLS AND WOMEN. TWENTY-ONE YOUTHS LEARNED HOW TO SEW 3 TYPES OF SKIRTS, SHIRTS , BLOUSES AND APRONS. NINETEEN YOUTHS TOOK CROCHET AND MADE BELTS, SMALL BAGS, AND BRACELETS. OTHER GROUPS ARE INVOLVED IN APPLIQUES AND SANDAL MAKING. CHRISTMAS AND EASTER BASKETS MANY FAMILIES LOST THEIR CROPS DUE TO RECENT DROUGHT AND TORRENTIAL RAIN DURING TWO PLANTING SEASON. WE DISTRIBUTED A BASKET OF FOOD TO 585 FAMILIES FOR EASTER. EACH BASKET CONTAINED 5LBS OF SUGAR, 5LBS OF RICE, 2 HERRINGS, 50 ML OF OIL, 4 HEADS OF GARLIC, 3 CUPS OF LAUNDRY DETERGENT, 8 OZ OF TOMATO PASTE, 1LB OF BUTTER, TWO BAGS OF SPAGHETTI, AND 3 BODY SOAPS. THE BASKETS WERE DISTRIBUTED TO THE MOST VULNERABLE FAMILIES IN EACH COMMUNITY. LAST YEAR WAS A VERY CHALLENGING YEAR FOR OUR PARTNER COMMUNITIES, ESPECIALLY FOR THE MOST VULNERABLE FAMILIES. DELIVERING A GIFT BASKET FOR CHRISTMAS TO 341 FAMILIES IN 12 COMMUNITIES WAS VERY APPRECIATED. SINCE PRICES OF FOOD ARE VERY EXPENSIVE, THE AMOUNT OF FOOD ITEMS WE USED TO GIVE WAS REDUCED. EVERYONE RECEIVED A NEW BASKET WITH: 6.5 LBS. OF RICE, 6.5LBS OF SUGAR, LITER OF OIL,1 SMALL BOWL OF BUTTER, 2-3 BAGS OF TOMATO PASTE, 2 BODY SOAP, 1-2 HERRINGS, 3 CUPS OF POWDER DETERGENT, 4 HEADS OF GARLIC, AND 2 SPAGHETTIS. BECAUSE OF THE CHALLENGING YEAR WE HAD AT ALL LEVELS IN THE COUNTRY THIS YEAR, WE DID NOT THINK THE CELEBRATION WOULD TAKE PLACE FOR THE CHILDREN. IT WAS WITH A LOT OF DIFFICULTIES THAT MERCHANDISE GOT THROUGH TO THE SOUTHERN PART OF THE COUNTRY THUS MAKING HIGH DEMANDS FOR PRODUCTS. BUT WE WERE DETERMINED TO GET SOME GIFTS FOR THE KIDS ESPECIALLY DURING THIS TOUGH YEAR. THE CHILDREN RECEIVED COSMETIC AND CLOTHING ITEMS: 1 TOOTHPASTE, 2 BODY SOAPS, 2 TOOTHBRUSHES, 1 SHAMPOO, 1 PERFUME, 1 BODY LOTION, 1 HAIR CONDITIONER AND 1 DEODORANT. IN ADDITION TO COSMETIC ITEMS, EACH BOY GOT 3 BOXERS,3 UNDERSHIRTS, 1 PAIR OF PANTS, 1 POLO SHIRT; AND EACH GIRL WAS GIFTED 1 BEAUTIFUL DRESS, 1 JEAN SKIRT, AND UNDERWEAR. KIDS AND PARENTS CELEBRATED WITH FOOD, DRINKS AND SANG CHRISTMAS SONGS. "THANK YOU FOR THINKING ABOUT THE CHILDREN DURING THE HOLIDAY SEASON. THANK YOU FOR GIVING THEM JOYFUL MOMENTS DURING THIS DIFFICULT YEAR. MAY GOD BLESS YOU AND WISHING YOU A GREAT 2023 YEAR". MARIE JOSE LEGOUT, FONDATION COFHED HATI STAFF.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>FORM 990, PART VI, SECTION A, LINE 2</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR/BOARD MEMBER NICAISE AVIGNON IS RELATED TO BOARD MEMBER MATT AVIGNON PETERSEN (SON-IN-LAW) WHO DID NOT GET PAID FOR GOODS OR SERVICES RENDERED. MADELEINE AVIGNON, NICAISE AVIGNON'S WIFE, AND NORKA AVIGNON-PETERSON (DAUGHTER), ARE EMPLOYEES OF COFHED.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>FORM 990, PART VI, SECTION B, LINE 11B</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>THE BOARD OF DIRECTORS APPROVE THE 990 PRIOR TO FILING.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>FORM 990, PART VI, SECTION B, LINE 12C</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>COMPLIANCE AND MONITORING IS PERFORMED AT BOARD MEETINGS.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>FORM 990, PART VI, SECTION B, LINE 15</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>COMPENSATION IS DETERMINED BY COMPARATIVE DATA OF COMPARABLE POSITIONS IN THE SAME OR SIMILAR PROFESSIONS. THE COMPENSATION IS REVIEWED AND APPROVED BY THE BOARD OF DIRECTORS.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>FORM 990, PART VI, SECTION C, LINE 19</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>AVAILABLE UPON REQUEST</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>FORM 990, PART IX, LINE 24E</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>TRAIN THE TRAINER: PROGRAM SERVICE EXPENSES 17,243. MANAGEMENT AND GENERAL EXPENSES 0. FUNDRAISING EXPENSES 0. TOTAL EXPENSES 17,243. SUPPORT OPERATIONS: PROGRAM SERVICE EXPENSES 2,315. MANAGEMENT AND GENERAL EXPENSES 6,064. FUNDRAISING EXPENSES 2,789. TOTAL EXPENSES 11,168. PROGRAM OPERATIONS: PROGRAM SERVICE EXPENSES 9,608. MANAGEMENT AND GENERAL EXPENSES 0. FUNDRAISING EXPENSES 0. TOTAL EXPENSES 9,608. RELIEF EFFORTS: PROGRAM SERVICE EXPENSES 8,615. MANAGEMENT AND GENERAL EXPENSES 0. FUNDRAISING EXPENSES 0. TOTAL EXPENSES 8,615. COMMUNITY INFRASTRUCTURE: PROGRAM SERVICE EXPENSES 8,411. MANAGEMENT AND GENERAL EXPENSES 0. FUNDRAISING EXPENSES 0. TOTAL EXPENSES 8,411. DEVELOPMENT: PROGRAM SERVICE EXPENSES 0. MANAGEMENT AND GENERAL EXPENSES 0. FUNDRAISING EXPENSES 5,437. TOTAL EXPENSES 5,437. SERVICE FEES: PROGRAM SERVICE EXPENSES 51. MANAGEMENT AND GENERAL EXPENSES 3,570. FUNDRAISING EXPENSES 1,031. TOTAL EXPENSES 4,652. HEALTH AND MEDICAL: PROGRAM SERVICE EXPENSES 2,192. MANAGEMENT AND GENERAL EXPENSES 0. FUNDRAISING EXPENSES 0. TOTAL EXPENSES 2,192. EMPLOYEE APPRECIATION: PROGRAM SERVICE EXPENSES 1,225. MANAGEMENT AND GENERAL EXPENSES 200. FUNDRAISING EXPENSES 0. TOTAL EXPENSES 1,425.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
    </IRS990ScheduleO>
    <IRS990ScheduleR documentId="RetDoc1043400001">
      <IdRelatedTaxExemptOrgGrp>
        <DisregardedEntityName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>FONDATION COFHED HAITI</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </DisregardedEntityName>
        <ForeignAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>ROUTE DE GAETAN 021 HT 8140</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>CAMPPERRIN</CityNm>
          <CountryCd>HA</CountryCd>
        </ForeignAddress>
        <PrimaryActivitiesTxt>SUPPORT COFHED ACTIVITIES IN HAITI</PrimaryActivitiesTxt>
        <LegalDomicileForeignCountryCd>HA</LegalDomicileForeignCountryCd>
        <DirectControllingNACd>N/A</DirectControllingNACd>
        <ControlledOrganizationInd>0</ControlledOrganizationInd>
      </IdRelatedTaxExemptOrgGrp>
      <ReceiptOfIntAnntsRntsRyltsInd>0</ReceiptOfIntAnntsRntsRyltsInd>
      <GiftGrntOrCapContriToOthOrgInd>1</GiftGrntOrCapContriToOthOrgInd>
      <GiftGrntCapContriFromOthOrgInd>0</GiftGrntCapContriFromOthOrgInd>
      <LoansOrGuaranteesToOtherOrgInd>0</LoansOrGuaranteesToOtherOrgInd>
      <LoansOrGuaranteesFromOthOrgInd>0</LoansOrGuaranteesFromOthOrgInd>
      <DivRelatedOrganizationInd>0</DivRelatedOrganizationInd>
      <AssetSaleToOtherOrgInd>0</AssetSaleToOtherOrgInd>
      <AssetPurchaseFromOtherOrgInd>0</AssetPurchaseFromOtherOrgInd>
      <AssetExchangeInd>0</AssetExchangeInd>
      <RentalOfFacilitiesToOthOrgInd>0</RentalOfFacilitiesToOthOrgInd>
      <RentalOfFcltsFromOthOrgInd>0</RentalOfFcltsFromOthOrgInd>
      <PerformOfServicesForOthOrgInd>0</PerformOfServicesForOthOrgInd>
      <PerformOfServicesByOtherOrgInd>0</PerformOfServicesByOtherOrgInd>
      <SharingOfFacilitiesInd>0</SharingOfFacilitiesInd>
      <PaidEmployeesSharingInd>0</PaidEmployeesSharingInd>
      <ReimbursementPaidToOtherOrgInd>0</ReimbursementPaidToOtherOrgInd>
      <ReimbursementPaidByOtherOrgInd>0</ReimbursementPaidByOtherOrgInd>
      <TransferToOtherOrgInd>0</TransferToOtherOrgInd>
      <TransferFromOtherOrgInd>0</TransferFromOtherOrgInd>
      <TransactionsRelatedOrgGrp>
        <OtherOrganizationName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>FONDATION COFHED HAITI</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </OtherOrganizationName>
        <TransactionTypeTxt>B</TransactionTypeTxt>
        <InvolvedAmt>273307</InvolvedAmt>
        <MethodOfAmountDeterminationTxt>CASH</MethodOfAmountDeterminationTxt>
      </TransactionsRelatedOrgGrp>
    </IRS990ScheduleR>
  </ReturnData>
</Return>
