<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Return xmlns="http://www.irs.gov/efile" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.irs.gov/efile" returnVersion="2022v5.0">
  <ReturnHeader binaryAttachmentCnt="0">
    <ReturnTs>2023-11-27T07:56:59-06:00</ReturnTs>
    <TaxPeriodEndDt>2023-06-30</TaxPeriodEndDt>
    <PreparerFirmGrp>
      <PreparerFirmEIN>591687531</PreparerFirmEIN>
      <PreparerFirmName>
        <BusinessNameLine1Txt>PDR CPAS Advisors</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
      </PreparerFirmName>
      <PreparerUSAddress>
        <AddressLine1Txt>4023 Tampa Road Suite 2000</AddressLine1Txt>
        <CityNm>Oldsmar</CityNm>
        <StateAbbreviationCd>FL</StateAbbreviationCd>
        <ZIPCd>34677</ZIPCd>
      </PreparerUSAddress>
    </PreparerFirmGrp>
    <ReturnTypeCd>990</ReturnTypeCd>
    <TaxPeriodBeginDt>2022-07-01</TaxPeriodBeginDt>
    <Filer>
      <EIN>112306416</EIN>
      <BusinessName>
        <BusinessNameLine1Txt>American Association of Kidney Patients</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        <BusinessNameLine2Txt>Inc</BusinessNameLine2Txt>
      </BusinessName>
      <BusinessNameControlTxt>AMER</BusinessNameControlTxt>
      <PhoneNum>8136368100</PhoneNum>
      <USAddress>
        <AddressLine1Txt>14440 Bruce B Downs Blvd</AddressLine1Txt>
        <CityNm>Tampa</CityNm>
        <StateAbbreviationCd>FL</StateAbbreviationCd>
        <ZIPCd>33613</ZIPCd>
      </USAddress>
    </Filer>
    <BusinessOfficerGrp>
      <PersonNm>Diana Clynes</PersonNm>
      <PersonTitleTxt>Executive Director</PersonTitleTxt>
      <PhoneNum>8136368100</PhoneNum>
      <SignatureDt>2023-11-08</SignatureDt>
      <DiscussWithPaidPreparerInd>1</DiscussWithPaidPreparerInd>
    </BusinessOfficerGrp>
    <SigningOfficerGrp>
      <PersonFullName>
        <PersonFirstNm>Diana</PersonFirstNm>
        <PersonLastNm>Clynes</PersonLastNm>
      </PersonFullName>
      <SSN>999009999</SSN>
    </SigningOfficerGrp>
    <IRSResponsiblePrtyInfoCurrInd>0</IRSResponsiblePrtyInfoCurrInd>
    <PreparerPersonGrp>
      <PreparerPersonNm>Mary Brown</PreparerPersonNm>
      <PTIN>P01892845</PTIN>
      <PhoneNum>7277854447</PhoneNum>
      <PreparationDt>2023-11-06</PreparationDt>
    </PreparerPersonGrp>
    <AdditionalFilerInformation>
      <TrustedCustomerGrp>
        <TrustedCustomerCd>2</TrustedCustomerCd>
        <AuthenticationAssuranceLevelCd>AAL1</AuthenticationAssuranceLevelCd>
        <IdentityAssuranceLevelCd>IAL1</IdentityAssuranceLevelCd>
      </TrustedCustomerGrp>
    </AdditionalFilerInformation>
    <TaxYr>2022</TaxYr>
    <BuildTS>2023-04-26 12:10:37Z</BuildTS>
  </ReturnHeader>
  <ReturnData documentCnt="7">
    <IRS990 documentId="RetDoc1038000001" referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1044400001">
      <PrincipalOfficerNm>Diana Clynes</PrincipalOfficerNm>
      <USAddress>
        <AddressLine1Txt>14440 Bruce B Downs Blvd</AddressLine1Txt>
        <CityNm>Tampa</CityNm>
        <StateAbbreviationCd>FL</StateAbbreviationCd>
        <ZIPCd>33613</ZIPCd>
      </USAddress>
      <GrossReceiptsAmt>2696486</GrossReceiptsAmt>
      <GroupReturnForAffiliatesInd>0</GroupReturnForAffiliatesInd>
      <Organization501c3Ind>X</Organization501c3Ind>
      <WebsiteAddressTxt>www.aakp.org</WebsiteAddressTxt>
      <TypeOfOrganizationCorpInd>X</TypeOfOrganizationCorpInd>
      <FormationYr>1969</FormationYr>
      <LegalDomicileStateCd>FL</LegalDomicileStateCd>
      <ActivityOrMissionDesc>AAKP is dedicated to improving the lives and long-term outcome of kidney patients. Cont on Sch O.</ActivityOrMissionDesc>
      <VotingMembersGoverningBodyCnt>14</VotingMembersGoverningBodyCnt>
      <VotingMembersIndependentCnt>14</VotingMembersIndependentCnt>
      <TotalEmployeeCnt>7</TotalEmployeeCnt>
      <TotalVolunteersCnt>200</TotalVolunteersCnt>
      <TotalGrossUBIAmt>0</TotalGrossUBIAmt>
      <NetUnrelatedBusTxblIncmAmt>0</NetUnrelatedBusTxblIncmAmt>
      <PYContributionsGrantsAmt>1944903</PYContributionsGrantsAmt>
      <CYContributionsGrantsAmt>1857222</CYContributionsGrantsAmt>
      <PYProgramServiceRevenueAmt>531891</PYProgramServiceRevenueAmt>
      <CYProgramServiceRevenueAmt>817181</CYProgramServiceRevenueAmt>
      <PYInvestmentIncomeAmt>0</PYInvestmentIncomeAmt>
      <CYInvestmentIncomeAmt>17657</CYInvestmentIncomeAmt>
      <PYOtherRevenueAmt>-3856</PYOtherRevenueAmt>
      <CYOtherRevenueAmt>-13869</CYOtherRevenueAmt>
      <PYTotalRevenueAmt>2472938</PYTotalRevenueAmt>
      <CYTotalRevenueAmt>2678191</CYTotalRevenueAmt>
      <PYGrantsAndSimilarPaidAmt>8754</PYGrantsAndSimilarPaidAmt>
      <CYGrantsAndSimilarPaidAmt>19815</CYGrantsAndSimilarPaidAmt>
      <PYBenefitsPaidToMembersAmt>0</PYBenefitsPaidToMembersAmt>
      <CYBenefitsPaidToMembersAmt>0</CYBenefitsPaidToMembersAmt>
      <PYSalariesCompEmpBnftPaidAmt>623647</PYSalariesCompEmpBnftPaidAmt>
      <CYSalariesCompEmpBnftPaidAmt>747582</CYSalariesCompEmpBnftPaidAmt>
      <PYTotalProfFndrsngExpnsAmt>0</PYTotalProfFndrsngExpnsAmt>
      <CYTotalProfFndrsngExpnsAmt>0</CYTotalProfFndrsngExpnsAmt>
      <CYTotalFundraisingExpenseAmt>43494</CYTotalFundraisingExpenseAmt>
      <PYOtherExpensesAmt>944844</PYOtherExpensesAmt>
      <CYOtherExpensesAmt>1364636</CYOtherExpensesAmt>
      <PYTotalExpensesAmt>1577245</PYTotalExpensesAmt>
      <CYTotalExpensesAmt>2132033</CYTotalExpensesAmt>
      <PYRevenuesLessExpensesAmt>895693</PYRevenuesLessExpensesAmt>
      <CYRevenuesLessExpensesAmt>546158</CYRevenuesLessExpensesAmt>
      <TotalAssetsBOYAmt>2636113</TotalAssetsBOYAmt>
      <TotalAssetsEOYAmt>3117129</TotalAssetsEOYAmt>
      <TotalLiabilitiesBOYAmt>712787</TotalLiabilitiesBOYAmt>
      <TotalLiabilitiesEOYAmt>647645</TotalLiabilitiesEOYAmt>
      <NetAssetsOrFundBalancesBOYAmt>1923326</NetAssetsOrFundBalancesBOYAmt>
      <NetAssetsOrFundBalancesEOYAmt>2469484</NetAssetsOrFundBalancesEOYAmt>
      <InfoInScheduleOPartIIIInd>X</InfoInScheduleOPartIIIInd>
      <MissionDesc>See Schedule O</MissionDesc>
      <SignificantNewProgramSrvcInd>0</SignificantNewProgramSrvcInd>
      <SignificantChangeInd>0</SignificantChangeInd>
      <ExpenseAmt>674314</ExpenseAmt>
      <Desc>AAKP Center for Patient Engagement and AdvocacyThe AAKP has been a national leader in patient advocacy and education for over 50 years - and is the largest fully independent and patient-governed organization in the kidney ecosystem. AAKP is highly regarded across the Federal government among both career and appointed policymakers and our influence in the Executive Branch and the U.S. Congress transfers across transitions and elections cycles due to our massive network of relationships and long-held reputation as an independent voice for patients. AAKP believes that patients and industry must be at the table together and engaged at all levels of decision-making whenever the Federal government seeks to implement wide-ranging initiatives that impact innovation and shape future access</Desc>
      <ProgSrvcAccomActy2Grp>
        <ExpenseAmt>523797</ExpenseAmt>
        <GrantAmt>19815</GrantAmt>
        <RevenueAmt>24766</RevenueAmt>
        <Desc>Patient ServicesAAKP is dedicated to improving the lives and long-term outcome of kidney patients through education, advocacy, patient engagement and the fostering of patient communities. AAKP fights for early disease detection and appropriate diagnosis of rare/genetic conditions; increased kidney transplantation and pre-emptive transplantation; full patient choice of either in-center or home dialysis; protection of the patient/physician relationship; promotion of research and innovation including artificial wearable and implantable kidneys and xenotransplantation; and the elimination of barriers for patient access to available treatment options. At AAKP, we1. Educate: patients &amp; caregivers on important issues so patients can better understand their condition and make informed decisions on their care options which align with their life's goals and aspirations. AAKP is a recognized leader for patient-centered education - continually developing high quality, professionally written, edited and reviewed material.2. Advocate: for policies that improve treatment and extend life for kidney disease patients - always defending patient choice. AAKP has been the independent patient voice - advocating for improved access to high-quality healthcare through regulatory and legislative reform at the Federal level. The Association's work has improved long-term outcomes in both quality of health and the ability for patients and family members affected by kidney diseases to lead a more productive and meaningful life.3. Define: "patient engagement" as a substantive tool to impact policy &amp; health outcomes.4. Community: AAKP is leading the effort to bring kidney patients together to promote community, conversations and to seek out services that help maximize patients' everyday lives.AAKP operates via key distinctives and principles: 1. Elevate patient voice in national issues and across drug, diagnostic and device development2. Protect the unique relationship between patients and their doctors3. Educate patients and preserve their access to choices as informed consumers of healthcare4. Maintain full independence in all national policy and decisions - never surrender your letterhead5. Honor the principle of "no surprises" among trusted allies and Federal government officials AAKP services kidney patients across the disease spectrum, including those with risk factors for kidney diseases, individuals with early stage kidney disease to individuals with end stage kidney disease/kidney failure requiring a form of kidney replacement therapy such as dialysis or a kidney transplant. AAKP is proud to represent the largest base of kidney patients consumers and their care partners. The following major programs and initiatives are key to AAKP's service to the kidney patient community: Association web page, Association social media platforms and other digital communication tactics, Decade of the Kidney, AAKP Global, Patient Voice Patient Choice, AAKP Action Center, Ambassador Initiative (National and International), Signature Programs (including Global Summit on Kidney Disease Innovations, Policy Summit, National Patient Meeting, Policy Roundtables, Fun Walk), and educational programming/resources.</Desc>
      </ProgSrvcAccomActy2Grp>
      <ProgSrvcAccomActy3Grp>
        <ExpenseAmt>302498</ExpenseAmt>
        <RevenueAmt>384825</RevenueAmt>
        <Desc>Patient Information and Education AAKP firmly believes, as research has also shown, that patient and family member/caregiver education is an integral part of treatment and enhancing quality of life. Not educating a patient and their care partner about their condition and treatment options leaves the patient at risk for complications as well as the possibility of not selecting a course of treatment best suited for them. Education is a simple and effective way to improve overall health and achieve better outcomes.In the same vein, AAKP is uniquely positioned to ensure the patient has a central role in research and other activities that are designed to determine optimal approaches and strategies for providing healthcare services, assistance programs, access to new products and services, etc. AAKP constituents represent all ages, modalities, ethnicities, disease states, and a variety of demographic indicators. AAKP's research capabilities have grown rapidly, and the Association has created a sophisticated database and expansive social media channels which allow AAKP to better connect and learn from its constituents. In turn, AAKP provides education to patients and caregivers on what it means to be involved in research initiatives as well as opportunities to get involved. From online surveys, interviews, focus groups, and clinical trial awareness campaigns - AAKP is focused on inserting important patient insight and preferences into research to help inform innovation, advance care, and make a meaningful impact to improve lives - this means AAKP members are helping shape the future policies and discoveries that characterize kidney care!AAKP is known within the renal community as a leader in quality education; taking time to produce programs and materials that are current, relevant and address the most pressing issues patients and their families face. AAKP is deliberate in its development of educational programs, working closely with its Medical Advisory Board, health educators and fellow patients to create unbiased, reliable resources that are easily understood and beneficial to patients. AAKP routinely uses matrices to measure program outcomes to assess effectiveness and success as well as opportunities for enhancement. The AAKP fulfills our educational mission through an extensive patient education program to inform and educate kidney patients, their families, and the general public on kidney diseases. To meet the needs of all individuals, AAKP offers its programs in a variety of mediums: print, web-based and live (in-person). AAKP services more than one million individuals annually via its various educational programs and communication platforms. AAKP's bimonthly magazine, aakpRENALIFE, averages more than 400,000 readers/views annually and includes information about the latest news, education, policy/legislative issues, innovations/research occurring in the kidney community and patient/caregiver/living donor profiles. The magazine is also distributed to over 7,000 dialysis centers nationwide and has a substantial afterlife as it remains in dialysis centers for quite some time after mailing. aakpRENALIFE is available via print/digital medium and is archived on www.aakp.org for a term of one year.AAKP's monthly e-newsletters, collectively, were delivered more than 250,000 times during this year - including aakpRENALFLASH (designed for individuals on dialysis); Kidney Transplant Today (designed for individuals with or interested in a kidney transplant); Kidney Beginnings (designed for and new patients learning more about their disease; At Home with AAKP (designed for individuals on or interested in home dialysis therapies) and AAKP Pediatric Kidney Patients (designed for peds, adolescents and their families). AAKP hosts its monthly HealthLine and HealthLine Innovator webinar series for patients and the public on timely and relevant topics such as managing risk factors for kidney disease (diabetes/hypertension); understanding dialysis options; kidney transplantation; how to choose/change treatment options; diet/nutrition; importance of exercise; coping with a chronic illness, advocacy and social media; and more. These webinars are recorded and made available OnDemand to accommodate all schedules and needs and reach thousands annually. AAKP has expanded this webinar program to include an Innovator series, which highlights the latest research and innovation occurring in the kidney space.AAKP utilizes a variety of communication platforms to reach approximately one million individuals annually. Included in that reach is AAKP's social medial platforms: Facebook, Twitter, LinkedIn, Instagram, and YouTube Channel. AAKP's website (www.aakp.org) has over 420,000-page views annually. The website features the AAKP Center for Patient Research and Education and Center for Patient Engagement and Advocacy - including:" education (CKD, dialysis, transplant, co-related health conditions; causes of kidney disease; rare disease; nutrition); clinical trials/market research opportunities; Action Center (advocacy initiatives; policy issues; voter registration); patient engagement (Ambassador Initiative; Speakers Bureau; Veterans Health initiative; KidneyWorks; Support Groups), programs/events (National Patient Meeting; Cystinosis Scholarship Program, Medal of Excellence; Policy Summit; Global Summit; Patient Safety Program), and online store to download/purchase materials.National Awards ProgramAAKP's awards encompass three major categories. The first category includes Legacy Awards - awards that AAKP has extended to organizations and professionals for several decades. The second category encompasses Patient Engagement and Advocacy Awards - awards created over the course of the past several years through AAKP's new Center for Patient Engagement and Advocacy as a means of recognizing the increased influence patients have on national policymakers and healthcare deliberations. The third category includes Global Award recognitions. Global Award:Global Kidney Leadership and Innovation Award2023 Honoree: The Honorable Alex M. Azar, II, 24th U.S. Secretary of Health and Human Services (2018-2021)Legacy Awards:President's Award Presented to an individual who made a long-term commitment toward advancement and evolvement of AAKP's national strategy.Samuel J. Orenstein Award Presented to an individual who consistently renders extraordinary service toward the achievement of AAKP's goals, objectives and national strategy. Peter Lundin, MD Award Presented to a renal physician who has made contributions to the care, welfare and well-being of patients over a lifetime of devoted service.Dominick Gentile, MD Memorial Award Presented to an ESRD Network that has developed and maintained a program which has significantly benefited patients and demonstrated sustainability.Kidney Patient Support Group of the YearPresented to a kidney patient support group that has been active within their local community. This support group should have hosted community educational programs and activities to support its local patients and raise awareness of kidney disease.Patient Engagement and Advocacy Awards:National Social Media Education and Advocacy AwardPresented to an individual and organization each who has demonstrated a national level of excellence through social media to either educate or advocate on behalf of kidney patients and their loved ones in the areas of disease awareness, policy advocacy or the creation of online communities. This highly competitive award will recognize excellence on a variety of social media platforms and will include video, bloggers and social media content and sites that have grown large audiences through creative and effective use of social media. National Patient Engagement and Advocacy AwardPresented to an individual, organization and public servant each who are recognized leaders in the field of kidney patient education and advocacy and whose body of professional work and commitment to advance the interests of kidney patients through policy, education or activism. National Journalism AwardPresented to a reporter or journalist whose work in either print, online, television or web arena(s) has brought the needs and interests of the kidney patient community to the national forefront through journalistic excellence. Presented either for a single compelling story with local, regional or national significance, or body of work, which over time has informed Americans of the critical needs and concerns of the kidney patient community.</Desc>
      </ProgSrvcAccomActy3Grp>
      <ProgSrvcAccomActyOtherGrp>
        <ExpenseAmt>233635</ExpenseAmt>
        <RevenueAmt>409455</RevenueAmt>
        <Desc>See Schedule O</Desc>
      </ProgSrvcAccomActyOtherGrp>
      <TotalOtherProgSrvcExpenseAmt>233635</TotalOtherProgSrvcExpenseAmt>
      <TotalOtherProgSrvcRevenueAmt>409455</TotalOtherProgSrvcRevenueAmt>
      <TotalProgramServiceExpensesAmt>1734244</TotalProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      <DescribedInSection501c3Ind referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1039100001">1</DescribedInSection501c3Ind>
      <ScheduleBRequiredInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1234500001">1</ScheduleBRequiredInd>
      <PoliticalCampaignActyInd>0</PoliticalCampaignActyInd>
      <LobbyingActivitiesInd>0</LobbyingActivitiesInd>
      <SubjectToProxyTaxInd>0</SubjectToProxyTaxInd>
      <DonorAdvisedFundInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</DonorAdvisedFundInd>
      <ConservationEasementsInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</ConservationEasementsInd>
      <CollectionsOfArtInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</CollectionsOfArtInd>
      <CreditCounselingInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</CreditCounselingInd>
      <DonorRstrOrQuasiEndowmentsInd>0</DonorRstrOrQuasiEndowmentsInd>
      <ReportLandBuildingEquipmentInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">1</ReportLandBuildingEquipmentInd>
      <ReportInvestmentsOtherSecInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</ReportInvestmentsOtherSecInd>
      <ReportProgramRelatedInvstInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</ReportProgramRelatedInvstInd>
      <ReportOtherAssetsInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</ReportOtherAssetsInd>
      <ReportOtherLiabilitiesInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">1</ReportOtherLiabilitiesInd>
      <IncludeFIN48FootnoteInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">1</IncludeFIN48FootnoteInd>
      <IndependentAuditFinclStmtInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">1</IndependentAuditFinclStmtInd>
      <ConsolidatedAuditFinclStmtInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</ConsolidatedAuditFinclStmtInd>
      <SchoolOperatingInd>0</SchoolOperatingInd>
      <ForeignOfficeInd>0</ForeignOfficeInd>
      <ForeignActivitiesInd>0</ForeignActivitiesInd>
      <MoreThan5000KToOrgInd>0</MoreThan5000KToOrgInd>
      <MoreThan5000KToIndividualsInd>0</MoreThan5000KToIndividualsInd>
      <ProfessionalFundraisingInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1041300001">0</ProfessionalFundraisingInd>
      <FundraisingActivitiesInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1041300001">1</FundraisingActivitiesInd>
      <GamingActivitiesInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1041300001">0</GamingActivitiesInd>
      <OperateHospitalInd>0</OperateHospitalInd>
      <GrantsToOrganizationsInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1041900001">0</GrantsToOrganizationsInd>
      <GrantsToIndividualsInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1041900001">1</GrantsToIndividualsInd>
      <ScheduleJRequiredInd>0</ScheduleJRequiredInd>
      <TaxExemptBondsInd>0</TaxExemptBondsInd>
      <EngagedInExcessBenefitTransInd>0</EngagedInExcessBenefitTransInd>
      <PYExcessBenefitTransInd>0</PYExcessBenefitTransInd>
      <LoanOutstandingInd>0</LoanOutstandingInd>
      <GrantToRelatedPersonInd>0</GrantToRelatedPersonInd>
      <BusinessRlnWithOrgMemInd>0</BusinessRlnWithOrgMemInd>
      <BusinessRlnWithFamMemInd>0</BusinessRlnWithFamMemInd>
      <BusinessRlnWith35CtrlEntInd>0</BusinessRlnWith35CtrlEntInd>
      <DeductibleNonCashContriInd>0</DeductibleNonCashContriInd>
      <DeductibleArtContributionInd>0</DeductibleArtContributionInd>
      <TerminateOperationsInd>0</TerminateOperationsInd>
      <PartialLiquidationInd>0</PartialLiquidationInd>
      <DisregardedEntityInd>0</DisregardedEntityInd>
      <RelatedEntityInd>0</RelatedEntityInd>
      <RelatedOrganizationCtrlEntInd>0</RelatedOrganizationCtrlEntInd>
      <TrnsfrExmptNonChrtblRltdOrgInd>0</TrnsfrExmptNonChrtblRltdOrgInd>
      <ActivitiesConductedPrtshpInd>0</ActivitiesConductedPrtshpInd>
      <ScheduleORequiredInd>1</ScheduleORequiredInd>
      <IRPDocumentCnt>13</IRPDocumentCnt>
      <IRPDocumentW2GCnt>0</IRPDocumentW2GCnt>
      <BackupWthldComplianceInd>1</BackupWthldComplianceInd>
      <EmployeeCnt>7</EmployeeCnt>
      <EmploymentTaxReturnsFiledInd>1</EmploymentTaxReturnsFiledInd>
      <UnrelatedBusIncmOverLimitInd>0</UnrelatedBusIncmOverLimitInd>
      <ForeignFinancialAccountInd>0</ForeignFinancialAccountInd>
      <ProhibitedTaxShelterTransInd>0</ProhibitedTaxShelterTransInd>
      <TaxablePartyNotificationInd>0</TaxablePartyNotificationInd>
      <NondeductibleContributionsInd>0</NondeductibleContributionsInd>
      <QuidProQuoContributionsInd>0</QuidProQuoContributionsInd>
      <Form8282PropertyDisposedOfInd>0</Form8282PropertyDisposedOfInd>
      <IndoorTanningServicesInd>0</IndoorTanningServicesInd>
      <SubjToTaxRmnrtnExPrchtPymtInd>0</SubjToTaxRmnrtnExPrchtPymtInd>
      <SubjectToExcsTaxNetInvstIncInd>0</SubjectToExcsTaxNetInvstIncInd>
      <InfoInScheduleOPartVIInd>X</InfoInScheduleOPartVIInd>
      <GoverningBodyVotingMembersCnt>14</GoverningBodyVotingMembersCnt>
      <IndependentVotingMemberCnt>14</IndependentVotingMemberCnt>
      <FamilyOrBusinessRlnInd>0</FamilyOrBusinessRlnInd>
      <DelegationOfMgmtDutiesInd>0</DelegationOfMgmtDutiesInd>
      <ChangeToOrgDocumentsInd>0</ChangeToOrgDocumentsInd>
      <MaterialDiversionOrMisuseInd>0</MaterialDiversionOrMisuseInd>
      <MembersOrStockholdersInd>0</MembersOrStockholdersInd>
      <ElectionOfBoardMembersInd>0</ElectionOfBoardMembersInd>
      <DecisionsSubjectToApprovaInd>0</DecisionsSubjectToApprovaInd>
      <MinutesOfGoverningBodyInd>1</MinutesOfGoverningBodyInd>
      <MinutesOfCommitteesInd>1</MinutesOfCommitteesInd>
      <OfficerMailingAddressInd>0</OfficerMailingAddressInd>
      <LocalChaptersInd>0</LocalChaptersInd>
      <Form990ProvidedToGvrnBodyInd>1</Form990ProvidedToGvrnBodyInd>
      <ConflictOfInterestPolicyInd>1</ConflictOfInterestPolicyInd>
      <AnnualDisclosureCoveredPrsnInd>1</AnnualDisclosureCoveredPrsnInd>
      <RegularMonitoringEnfrcInd>1</RegularMonitoringEnfrcInd>
      <WhistleblowerPolicyInd>1</WhistleblowerPolicyInd>
      <DocumentRetentionPolicyInd>1</DocumentRetentionPolicyInd>
      <CompensationProcessCEOInd>1</CompensationProcessCEOInd>
      <CompensationProcessOtherInd>0</CompensationProcessOtherInd>
      <InvestmentInJointVentureInd>0</InvestmentInJointVentureInd>
      <StatesWhereCopyOfReturnIsFldCd>FL</StatesWhereCopyOfReturnIsFldCd>
      <OwnWebsiteInd>X</OwnWebsiteInd>
      <OtherWebsiteInd>X</OtherWebsiteInd>
      <UponRequestInd>X</UponRequestInd>
      <BooksInCareOfDetail>
        <BusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>Diana Clynes</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </BusinessName>
        <PhoneNum>8136368100</PhoneNum>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>14440 Bruce B Downs Blvd</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>Tampa</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>FL</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>33613</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
      </BooksInCareOfDetail>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>Richard Knight</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Past President</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <OfficerInd>X</OfficerInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>Edward V Hickey III</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>President</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <OfficerInd>X</OfficerInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>Suzanne Ruff</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Treasurer</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <OfficerInd>X</OfficerInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>Dale Rogers</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Secretary</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <OfficerInd>X</OfficerInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>Kent Bressler MA RN</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Board Member</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>Jennifer L Jones</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Vice President</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <OfficerInd>X</OfficerInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>Paul T Conway</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Board Member</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>Sara E Schaffer MBA MA RD</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Board Member</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>Barry H Smith MD PhD</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Board Member</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>Janice Lea MD MSC FASN</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Board Member</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>James W Myers III</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Board Member</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>David Rodriquez</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Board Member</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>Lana Schmidt MBA</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Board Member</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>Catherine Campbell DNP RN MBA</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Board Member</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>Diana Clynes</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Executive Director</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>37.50</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <OfficerInd>X</OfficerInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>150000</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>Erin Kahle</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Deputy Director</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>37.50</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <HighestCompensatedEmployeeInd>X</HighestCompensatedEmployeeInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>115000</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>Jerome Bailey</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Director of Patient Engagement</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>37.50</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <HighestCompensatedEmployeeInd>X</HighestCompensatedEmployeeInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>110000</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <TotalReportableCompFromOrgAmt>375000</TotalReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
      <TotReportableCompRltdOrgAmt>0</TotReportableCompRltdOrgAmt>
      <TotalOtherCompensationAmt>0</TotalOtherCompensationAmt>
      <IndivRcvdGreaterThan100KCnt>3</IndivRcvdGreaterThan100KCnt>
      <FormerOfcrEmployeesListedInd>0</FormerOfcrEmployeesListedInd>
      <TotalCompGreaterThan150KInd>0</TotalCompGreaterThan150KInd>
      <CompensationFromOtherSrcsInd>0</CompensationFromOtherSrcsInd>
      <ContractorCompensationGrp>
        <ContractorName>
          <BusinessName>
            <BusinessNameLine1Txt>Briar Patch Media</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
          </BusinessName>
        </ContractorName>
        <ContractorAddress>
          <USAddress>
            <AddressLine1Txt>8054 Andiron Lane</AddressLine1Txt>
            <CityNm>Jessup</CityNm>
            <StateAbbreviationCd>MD</StateAbbreviationCd>
            <ZIPCd>20794</ZIPCd>
          </USAddress>
        </ContractorAddress>
        <ServicesDesc>Audio and video production</ServicesDesc>
        <CompensationAmt>320029</CompensationAmt>
      </ContractorCompensationGrp>
      <ContractorCompensationGrp>
        <ContractorName>
          <BusinessName>
            <BusinessNameLine1Txt>JK Strategies</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
          </BusinessName>
        </ContractorName>
        <ContractorAddress>
          <USAddress>
            <AddressLine1Txt>10306 Snowpine Way</AddressLine1Txt>
            <CityNm>Potomac</CityNm>
            <StateAbbreviationCd>MD</StateAbbreviationCd>
            <ZIPCd>20854</ZIPCd>
          </USAddress>
        </ContractorAddress>
        <ServicesDesc>Market research, event promotions, and c</ServicesDesc>
        <CompensationAmt>249996</CompensationAmt>
      </ContractorCompensationGrp>
      <ContractorCompensationGrp>
        <ContractorName>
          <BusinessName>
            <BusinessNameLine1Txt>Mail Marketing</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
          </BusinessName>
        </ContractorName>
        <ContractorAddress>
          <USAddress>
            <AddressLine1Txt>PO Box 17918</AddressLine1Txt>
            <CityNm>Clearwater</CityNm>
            <StateAbbreviationCd>FL</StateAbbreviationCd>
            <ZIPCd>33762</ZIPCd>
          </USAddress>
        </ContractorAddress>
        <ServicesDesc>Printing (brochures, magazine, flyers, l</ServicesDesc>
        <CompensationAmt>124662</CompensationAmt>
      </ContractorCompensationGrp>
      <ContractorCompensationGrp>
        <ContractorName>
          <BusinessName>
            <BusinessNameLine1Txt>Emory University Office of Grants and Co</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
          </BusinessName>
        </ContractorName>
        <ContractorAddress>
          <USAddress>
            <AddressLine1Txt>1599 Clifton Rd 4th Floor</AddressLine1Txt>
            <CityNm>Atlanta</CityNm>
            <StateAbbreviationCd>GA</StateAbbreviationCd>
            <ZIPCd>30322</ZIPCd>
          </USAddress>
        </ContractorAddress>
        <ServicesDesc>Analysis of genetic testing and data for</ServicesDesc>
        <CompensationAmt>102465</CompensationAmt>
      </ContractorCompensationGrp>
      <CntrctRcvdGreaterThan100KCnt>4</CntrctRcvdGreaterThan100KCnt>
      <MembershipDuesAmt>588980</MembershipDuesAmt>
      <FundraisingAmt>35000</FundraisingAmt>
      <AllOtherContributionsAmt>1233242</AllOtherContributionsAmt>
      <TotalContributionsAmt>1857222</TotalContributionsAmt>
      <ProgramServiceRevenueGrp>
        <Desc>Annual Meeting</Desc>
        <BusinessCd>900099</BusinessCd>
        <TotalRevenueColumnAmt>409455</TotalRevenueColumnAmt>
        <RelatedOrExemptFuncIncomeAmt>409455</RelatedOrExemptFuncIncomeAmt>
      </ProgramServiceRevenueGrp>
      <ProgramServiceRevenueGrp>
        <Desc>Global Summit</Desc>
        <BusinessCd>900099</BusinessCd>
        <TotalRevenueColumnAmt>236075</TotalRevenueColumnAmt>
        <RelatedOrExemptFuncIncomeAmt>236075</RelatedOrExemptFuncIncomeAmt>
      </ProgramServiceRevenueGrp>
      <ProgramServiceRevenueGrp>
        <Desc>Policy Summit</Desc>
        <BusinessCd>900099</BusinessCd>
        <TotalRevenueColumnAmt>148750</TotalRevenueColumnAmt>
        <RelatedOrExemptFuncIncomeAmt>148750</RelatedOrExemptFuncIncomeAmt>
      </ProgramServiceRevenueGrp>
      <ProgramServiceRevenueGrp>
        <Desc>Inventory Sale</Desc>
        <BusinessCd>900099</BusinessCd>
        <TotalRevenueColumnAmt>22901</TotalRevenueColumnAmt>
        <RelatedOrExemptFuncIncomeAmt>22901</RelatedOrExemptFuncIncomeAmt>
      </ProgramServiceRevenueGrp>
      <TotalProgramServiceRevenueAmt>817181</TotalProgramServiceRevenueAmt>
      <InvestmentIncomeGrp>
        <TotalRevenueColumnAmt>17657</TotalRevenueColumnAmt>
        <ExclusionAmt>17657</ExclusionAmt>
      </InvestmentIncomeGrp>
      <FundraisingGrossIncomeAmt>2561</FundraisingGrossIncomeAmt>
      <ContriRptFundraisingEventAmt>35000</ContriRptFundraisingEventAmt>
      <FundraisingDirectExpensesAmt>18295</FundraisingDirectExpensesAmt>
      <NetIncmFromFundraisingEvtGrp>
        <TotalRevenueColumnAmt>-15734</TotalRevenueColumnAmt>
        <ExclusionAmt>-15734</ExclusionAmt>
      </NetIncmFromFundraisingEvtGrp>
      <OtherRevenueMiscGrp>
        <Desc>Other</Desc>
        <BusinessCd>900099</BusinessCd>
        <TotalRevenueColumnAmt>1865</TotalRevenueColumnAmt>
        <RelatedOrExemptFuncIncomeAmt>1865</RelatedOrExemptFuncIncomeAmt>
      </OtherRevenueMiscGrp>
      <OtherRevenueTotalAmt>1865</OtherRevenueTotalAmt>
      <TotalRevenueGrp>
        <TotalRevenueColumnAmt>2678191</TotalRevenueColumnAmt>
        <RelatedOrExemptFuncIncomeAmt>819046</RelatedOrExemptFuncIncomeAmt>
        <UnrelatedBusinessRevenueAmt>0</UnrelatedBusinessRevenueAmt>
        <ExclusionAmt>1923</ExclusionAmt>
      </TotalRevenueGrp>
      <GrantsToDomesticIndividualsGrp>
        <TotalAmt>19815</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>19815</ProgramServicesAmt>
      </GrantsToDomesticIndividualsGrp>
      <CompCurrentOfcrDirectorsGrp>
        <TotalAmt>375000</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>248032</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>118686</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
        <FundraisingAmt>8282</FundraisingAmt>
      </CompCurrentOfcrDirectorsGrp>
      <CompDisqualPersonsGrp>
        <TotalAmt>267748</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>177093</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>84741</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
        <FundraisingAmt>5914</FundraisingAmt>
      </CompDisqualPersonsGrp>
      <OtherEmployeeBenefitsGrp>
        <TotalAmt>58145</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>38458</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>18403</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
        <FundraisingAmt>1284</FundraisingAmt>
      </OtherEmployeeBenefitsGrp>
      <PayrollTaxesGrp>
        <TotalAmt>46689</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>27978</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>17818</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
        <FundraisingAmt>893</FundraisingAmt>
      </PayrollTaxesGrp>
      <FeesForServicesLegalGrp>
        <TotalAmt>6450</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>5094</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>1356</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </FeesForServicesLegalGrp>
      <FeesForServicesAccountingGrp>
        <TotalAmt>36350</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>28711</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>7639</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </FeesForServicesAccountingGrp>
      <FeesForServicesOtherGrp>
        <TotalAmt>185281</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>146344</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>38937</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </FeesForServicesOtherGrp>
      <AdvertisingGrp>
        <TotalAmt>141377</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>141377</ProgramServicesAmt>
      </AdvertisingGrp>
      <OccupancyGrp>
        <TotalAmt>44212</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>29243</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>13993</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
        <FundraisingAmt>976</FundraisingAmt>
      </OccupancyGrp>
      <TravelGrp>
        <TotalAmt>70570</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>70496</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>74</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </TravelGrp>
      <DepreciationDepletionGrp>
        <TotalAmt>3616</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>2392</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>1144</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
        <FundraisingAmt>80</FundraisingAmt>
      </DepreciationDepletionGrp>
      <OtherExpensesGrp>
        <Desc>Annual meeting and prog</Desc>
        <TotalAmt>621145</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>621145</ProgramServicesAmt>
      </OtherExpensesGrp>
      <OtherExpensesGrp>
        <Desc>Printing and Publicatio</Desc>
        <TotalAmt>105605</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>103724</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>1881</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </OtherExpensesGrp>
      <OtherExpensesGrp>
        <Desc>Equipment rental and ma</Desc>
        <TotalAmt>78165</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>51700</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>24739</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
        <FundraisingAmt>1726</FundraisingAmt>
      </OtherExpensesGrp>
      <OtherExpensesGrp>
        <Desc>Postage and shipping</Desc>
        <TotalAmt>32223</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>19019</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>11901</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
        <FundraisingAmt>1303</FundraisingAmt>
      </OtherExpensesGrp>
      <AllOtherExpensesGrp>
        <TotalAmt>39642</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>3623</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>12983</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
        <FundraisingAmt>23036</FundraisingAmt>
      </AllOtherExpensesGrp>
      <TotalFunctionalExpensesGrp>
        <TotalAmt>2132033</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>1734244</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>354295</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
        <FundraisingAmt>43494</FundraisingAmt>
      </TotalFunctionalExpensesGrp>
      <CashNonInterestBearingGrp>
        <BOYAmt>2204420</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>2734808</EOYAmt>
      </CashNonInterestBearingGrp>
      <AccountsReceivableGrp>
        <BOYAmt>354066</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>199960</EOYAmt>
      </AccountsReceivableGrp>
      <InventoriesForSaleOrUseGrp>
        <BOYAmt>43589</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>55327</EOYAmt>
      </InventoriesForSaleOrUseGrp>
      <PrepaidExpensesDefrdChargesGrp>
        <BOYAmt>20838</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>31549</EOYAmt>
      </PrepaidExpensesDefrdChargesGrp>
      <LandBldgEquipCostOrOtherBssAmt>52983</LandBldgEquipCostOrOtherBssAmt>
      <LandBldgEquipAccumDeprecAmt>43651</LandBldgEquipAccumDeprecAmt>
      <LandBldgEquipBasisNetGrp>
        <BOYAmt>10075</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>9332</EOYAmt>
      </LandBldgEquipBasisNetGrp>
      <OtherAssetsTotalGrp>
        <BOYAmt>3125</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>86153</EOYAmt>
      </OtherAssetsTotalGrp>
      <TotalAssetsGrp>
        <BOYAmt>2636113</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>3117129</EOYAmt>
      </TotalAssetsGrp>
      <AccountsPayableAccrExpnssGrp>
        <BOYAmt>115660</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>107109</EOYAmt>
      </AccountsPayableAccrExpnssGrp>
      <DeferredRevenueGrp>
        <BOYAmt>597127</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>455222</EOYAmt>
      </DeferredRevenueGrp>
      <OtherLiabilitiesGrp>
        <BOYAmt>0</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>85314</EOYAmt>
      </OtherLiabilitiesGrp>
      <TotalLiabilitiesGrp>
        <BOYAmt>712787</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>647645</EOYAmt>
      </TotalLiabilitiesGrp>
      <OrganizationFollowsFASB117Ind>X</OrganizationFollowsFASB117Ind>
      <NoDonorRestrictionNetAssetsGrp>
        <BOYAmt>1745924</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>2329097</EOYAmt>
      </NoDonorRestrictionNetAssetsGrp>
      <DonorRestrictionNetAssetsGrp>
        <BOYAmt>177402</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>140387</EOYAmt>
      </DonorRestrictionNetAssetsGrp>
      <TotalNetAssetsFundBalanceGrp>
        <BOYAmt>1923326</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>2469484</EOYAmt>
      </TotalNetAssetsFundBalanceGrp>
      <TotLiabNetAssetsFundBalanceGrp>
        <BOYAmt>2636113</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>3117129</EOYAmt>
      </TotLiabNetAssetsFundBalanceGrp>
      <ReconcilationRevenueExpnssAmt>546158</ReconcilationRevenueExpnssAmt>
      <OtherChangesInNetAssetsAmt>0</OtherChangesInNetAssetsAmt>
      <MethodOfAccountingAccrualInd>X</MethodOfAccountingAccrualInd>
      <AccountantCompileOrReviewInd>0</AccountantCompileOrReviewInd>
      <FSAuditedInd>1</FSAuditedInd>
      <FSAuditedBasisGrp>
        <SeparateBasisFinclStmtInd>X</SeparateBasisFinclStmtInd>
      </FSAuditedBasisGrp>
      <AuditCommitteeInd>1</AuditCommitteeInd>
      <FederalGrantAuditRequiredInd>0</FederalGrantAuditRequiredInd>
    </IRS990>
    <IRS990ScheduleA documentId="RetDoc1039100001">
      <PublicOrganization170Ind>X</PublicOrganization170Ind>
      <GiftsGrantsContriRcvd170Grp>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>1151107</CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>990174</CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>1196542</CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>1944903</CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearAmt>1857222</CurrentTaxYearAmt>
        <TotalAmt>7139948</TotalAmt>
      </GiftsGrantsContriRcvd170Grp>
      <TotalCalendarYear170Grp>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>1151107</CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>990174</CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>1196542</CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>1944903</CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearAmt>1857222</CurrentTaxYearAmt>
        <TotalAmt>7139948</TotalAmt>
      </TotalCalendarYear170Grp>
      <PublicSupportTotal170Amt>7139948</PublicSupportTotal170Amt>
      <GrossInvestmentIncome170Grp>
        <CurrentTaxYearAmt>17657</CurrentTaxYearAmt>
        <TotalAmt>17657</TotalAmt>
      </GrossInvestmentIncome170Grp>
      <UnrelatedBusinessNetIncm170Grp>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>82732</CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>39648</CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>26852</CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>49535</CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearAmt>0</CurrentTaxYearAmt>
        <TotalAmt>198767</TotalAmt>
      </UnrelatedBusinessNetIncm170Grp>
      <OtherIncome170Grp>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>1471</CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>355</CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>1412</CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>1033</CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearAmt>1865</CurrentTaxYearAmt>
        <TotalAmt>6136</TotalAmt>
      </OtherIncome170Grp>
      <TotalSupportAmt>7362508</TotalSupportAmt>
      <GrossReceiptsRltdActivitiesAmt>817181</GrossReceiptsRltdActivitiesAmt>
      <PublicSupportCY170Pct>0.96980</PublicSupportCY170Pct>
      <PublicSupportPY170Pct>0.95670</PublicSupportPY170Pct>
      <ThirtyThrPctSuprtTestsCY170Ind>X</ThirtyThrPctSuprtTestsCY170Ind>
    </IRS990ScheduleA>
    <IRS990ScheduleB documentId="RetDoc1234500001">
      <ContributorInformationGrp>
        <ContributorNum>RESTRICTED</ContributorNum>
        <ContributorBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1>RESTRICTED</BusinessNameLine1>
        </ContributorBusinessName>
        <ContributorUSAddress>
          <AddressLine1>RESTRICTED</AddressLine1>
          <AddressLine2>RESTRICTED</AddressLine2>
          <City>RESTRICTED</City>
          <State>RESTRICTED</State>
          <ZIPCode>RESTRICTED</ZIPCode>
        </ContributorUSAddress>
        <TotalContributionsAmt>RESTRICTED</TotalContributionsAmt>
      </ContributorInformationGrp>
    </IRS990ScheduleB>
    <IRS990ScheduleD documentId="RetDoc1040000001">
      <EquipmentGrp>
        <OtherCostOrOtherBasisAmt>52983</OtherCostOrOtherBasisAmt>
        <DepreciationAmt>43651</DepreciationAmt>
        <BookValueAmt>9332</BookValueAmt>
      </EquipmentGrp>
      <TotalBookValueLandBuildingsAmt>9332</TotalBookValueLandBuildingsAmt>
      <OtherLiabilitiesOrgGrp>
        <Desc>Current portion of lease liabilities</Desc>
        <Amt>41878</Amt>
      </OtherLiabilitiesOrgGrp>
      <OtherLiabilitiesOrgGrp>
        <Desc>Long term portion of lease liabilities</Desc>
        <Amt>43436</Amt>
      </OtherLiabilitiesOrgGrp>
      <TotalLiabilityAmt>85314</TotalLiabilityAmt>
      <FootnoteTextInd>X</FootnoteTextInd>
      <TotalRevEtcAuditedFinclStmtAmt>2682546</TotalRevEtcAuditedFinclStmtAmt>
      <DonatedServicesAndUseFcltsAmt>4355</DonatedServicesAndUseFcltsAmt>
      <RevenueNotReportedAmt>4355</RevenueNotReportedAmt>
      <RevenueSubtotalAmt>2678191</RevenueSubtotalAmt>
      <RevenueNotReportedFinclStmtAmt>0</RevenueNotReportedFinclStmtAmt>
      <TotalRevenuePerForm990Amt>2678191</TotalRevenuePerForm990Amt>
      <TotExpnsEtcAuditedFinclStmtAmt>2136388</TotExpnsEtcAuditedFinclStmtAmt>
      <DonatedServicesUseFcltsAmt>4355</DonatedServicesUseFcltsAmt>
      <ExpensesNotReportedAmt>4355</ExpensesNotReportedAmt>
      <ExpensesSubtotalAmt>2132033</ExpensesSubtotalAmt>
      <ExpensesNotRptFinclStmtAmt>0</ExpensesNotRptFinclStmtAmt>
      <TotalExpensesPerForm990Amt>2132033</TotalExpensesPerForm990Amt>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>Part X, Line 2:</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>The Organization accounts for the effect of any uncertain tax positions based on a "more likely than not" threshold to the recognition of the tax positions being sustained based on the technical merits of the position under scrutiny by the applicable taxing authority. If a tax position or positions are deemed to result in uncertainties of those positions, the unrecognized tax benefit is estimated based on a "cumulative probability assessment" that aggregates the estimated tax liability for all uncertain tax positions. The Organization has identified its tax status as a tax-exempt entity as its only significant tax position; however, the Organization has determined that such tax position does not result in an uncertainty requiring recognition. The Organization is not currently under examination by any taxing jurisdiction. The Organization's federal returns are generally open for examination for three years following the date filed.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
    </IRS990ScheduleD>
    <IRS990ScheduleG documentId="RetDoc1041300001">
      <FundraisingEventInformationGrp>
        <Event1Nm>Medal of Excellance</Event1Nm>
        <GrossReceiptsEvent1Amt>15000</GrossReceiptsEvent1Amt>
        <CharitableContriEvent1Amt>15000</CharitableContriEvent1Amt>
        <OtherDirectExpensesEvent1Amt>10087</OtherDirectExpensesEvent1Amt>
        <Event2Nm>Annual Walk for Fun</Event2Nm>
        <GrossReceiptsEvent2Amt>22561</GrossReceiptsEvent2Amt>
        <CharitableContriEvent2Amt>20000</CharitableContriEvent2Amt>
        <GrossRevenueEvent2Amt>2561</GrossRevenueEvent2Amt>
        <OtherDirectExpensesEvent2Amt>8208</OtherDirectExpensesEvent2Amt>
        <GrossReceiptsTotalAmt>37561</GrossReceiptsTotalAmt>
        <CharitableContributionsTotAmt>35000</CharitableContributionsTotAmt>
        <GrossRevenueTotalEventsAmt>2561</GrossRevenueTotalEventsAmt>
        <OthDirectExpnssTotalEventsAmt>18295</OthDirectExpnssTotalEventsAmt>
        <DirectExpenseSummaryEventsAmt>18295</DirectExpenseSummaryEventsAmt>
        <NetIncomeSummaryAmt>-15734</NetIncomeSummaryAmt>
      </FundraisingEventInformationGrp>
    </IRS990ScheduleG>
    <IRS990ScheduleI documentId="RetDoc1041900001">
      <GrantRecordsMaintainedInd>0</GrantRecordsMaintainedInd>
      <GrantsOtherAsstToIndivInUSGrp>
        <GrantTypeTxt>Scholarships</GrantTypeTxt>
        <RecipientCnt>8</RecipientCnt>
        <CashGrantAmt>19815</CashGrantAmt>
      </GrantsOtherAsstToIndivInUSGrp>
    </IRS990ScheduleI>
    <IRS990ScheduleO documentId="RetDoc1044400001">
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>Form 990, Part I, Line 1</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>The American Association of Kidney Patients (AAKP) is the oldest and largest fully independent kidney patient organization in the U.S.A. Founded in 1969 by six dialysis patients, with doctor encouragement, our Founders helped create the End Stage Renal Disease (ESRD) program, saving over one million lives since 1973. Our skilled Patient Members, Board of Directors, and Patient Ambassadors serve as advocates in Washington, D.C., and online, so AAKP never uses professional lobbyists as substitutes for the independent patient voice. Mission: AAKP is dedicated to improving the lives and long-term outcomes of kidney patients through education, advocacy, patient engagement, and the fostering of patient communities. Vision: AAKP fights for early disease detection and the appropriate diagnosis of rare/genetic conditions; increased kidney transplantation and pre-emptive transplantation; full patient choice of either in-center or home dialysis; protection of the patient/physician relationship; promotion of research and innovation including artificial implantable and wearable kidneys and xenotransplantation; and the elimination of barriers for patient access to available treatment options. For over 50 years, AAKP has been driving policy discussions on kidney patient care choice and medical innovation. Over the past decade, AAKP patient advocates have helped advance lifetime transplant drug coverage for kidney transplant recipients (2020); the presidential Executive Order on Advancing American Kidney Health (2019) new job protections for living organ donors under the Family Medical Leave Act (FMLA) via the U.S. Department of Labor (2018); and Congressional legislation allowing HIV-positive organ transplants for HIV-positive patients (2013). AAKP has long highlighted kidney disease as both a healthcare issue and a workforce issue of national importance. Through education, advocacy, and allied partnerships, AAKP continues to address the needs of the WHOLE person impacted by kidney disease, including the need to work part-time or full-time in a career or trade of their choice so they have the means to pursue their independence and aspirations. AAKP represents kidney patients across the full disease spectrum, from individuals at-risk, to early-stage chronic kidney disease (CKD), to those experiencing end stage kidney failure (ESKD), and transplant patients. We are proud of the fact that patients, care partners, organ donors, and allied professionals have helped AAKP build the largest patient consumer and care partner base in the kidney community. Each day, AAKP works diligently to help protect and extend the lives of kidney patients across the country, reaching over one million individuals annually. Viewership for 2023 AAKP signature events and patient education programs exceeds 100,000 people across 100 countries and is growing rapidly. International and national program faculty has included a combined 166 medical practitioners, researchers, and patient experts. Since 1969, AAKP has been a patient-led organization driving policy discussions on kidney patient care choice and medical innovation. In 2018, AAKP established the first and largest U.S. kidney voter registration program, KidneyVoters. Over the past decade, AAKP patient advocates have helped advance lifetime transplant drug coverage for kidney transplant recipients (2020); new job protections for living organ donors under the Family Medical Leave Act (FMLA) via the U.S. Department of Labor (2018); and Congressional legislation allowing HIV-positive organ transplants for HIV-positive patients (2013).</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>Program Service Accomplishments Line 4a: AAKP Center for Patient Engagement</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>to care options for individuals affected by kidney diseases. AAKP fundamentally understands that kidney disease and the health and treatment of kidney patients pose a significant impact on the American taxpayer and the national economy. The cost of kidney disease alone invites constant and intense interest and concern within the Federal government and the U.S. Congress. The costs associated with the disease have spurred multiple Federal initiatives in the past several years designed to increase positive patient outcomes, reduce spending, and increase efficiencies. The move by the Federal government to examine and re-examine many of the cost-drivers within healthcare spending, and specifically within the ESRD program, represents a key reason why AAKP is working aggressively to build our capacities to raise the independent patient voice throughout the Federal policy-making process. In order for AAKP to maintain our leadership in protecting patient interests, and the overlapping interests among allies throughout the broader kidney community including the pharmaceutical industry and providers, we intend to grow our membership numbers, advance our National AAKP Ambassador Initiative, expand our reach internationally and equip kidney patients across the globe with proven and cost-effective training and technologies that make an impact on the policy process. The Center for Patient Engagement and Advocacy was created to leverage AAKP's increased profile and influence in the national public policy process and to expedite implementation of our national strategy to vastly expand patient involvement in the decisions impacting their health outcomes. The AAKP Center for Patient Engagement and Advocacy was created in 2014 to leverage AAKP's increased profile and influence in the national public policy process and to expedite implementation of our National Strategy to vastly expand patient involvement in the decisions that impact their health outcomes. The Center for Patient Engagement and Advocacy brings, under one focused area, all AAKP efforts to build patient and family/caregiver membership in AAKP as well as their participation in existing and emerging AAKP patient health engagement and advocacy programs. At the heart of this Center is the AAKP Ambassador Initiative, launched in 2017, the program has grown to more than 170 + Ambassadors across the U.S. In 2019, AAKP launched the AAKP Global, the global arm of this initiative, and now has Global Ambassadors in countries such as Ireland, Canada, Argentina, United Arab Emirates, Puerto Rico, and many more. Ambassadors are AAKP's most engaged volunteers who utilize their personal experiences and professional skills to contribute to both the AAKP mission and the larger kidney community based on their desire to serve a cause larger than themselves. These individuals also allow AAKP to expand our reach and resources to make a positive impact at the state and local level and globally. Major programs, initiatives, and campaigns within this Center also include The Decade of the Kidney, the Annual Global Summit on Kidney Innovation, the Annual Public Policy Summit, and the AAKP Action Center - which includes the AAKP KidneyVotervoter registration campaign and the AAKP Patient Voice Patient Choice initiative. Additionally, as part of the AAKP National Strategy, the Center for Patient Engagement and Advocacy works to engage, train, certify and deploy kidney patients in ways that are the most effective at elevating the patient voice within Federal policy-making circles. This includes critical times when national legislation, health program implementation, regulations or potential delays in the pharmaceutical approval process pose a concern to patient access to quality care or their future healthcare outcomes. AAKP is engaging and encouraging kidney patients and caregivers to participate in substantive opportunities for effective patient engagement and advocacy. To date, AAKP has developed and makes available OnDemand over a dozen Advocacy and Engagement Skills Training sessions. AAKP has a history of advocating on important issues affecting patients' care, choice and access to approved treatments, increased research and innovation, and much more. The Advocacy Program helps support initiatives such as: Capitol Hill Day visits, participation in meetings/seminars/conventions, public policy, Communication, research issues affecting patients and practical tools that explain how to be more effective advocates. In the past decade, AAKP patients have helped gain lifetime transplant drug coverage for kidney transplant recipients (2020); new patient-centered policies via the White House Executive Order on Advancing American Kidney Health (2019); new job protections for living organ donors from the U.S. Department of Labor (2018); and Congressional legislation allowing HIV-positive organ transplants for HIV-positive patients (2013).</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>Program Service Accomplishments Line 4c: Patient Information and Education</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>National Public Service Award Presented to a public servant whose body of professional work and commitment to advance the interests and well-being of the Nation's kidney patient population through policy, education and activism. Past awardees include Dr. Carolyn Neuland, the U.S. Food and Drug Administration; Dr. Priti Patel, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention; Dr. Robert Star, National Institute of Health; and Elena Balovlenkov, MS, RN, CHH, Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services; and Dr. Paul Kimmel, National Institute of Health. Medal of Excellence The AAKP Medal of Excellence honors health care professionals who have made significant contributions to the advancement and evolution of direct patient care; encouraged the expansion of the patient engagement model within the renal community; and enhanced the quality of life for kidney patients and their families. The 2023 Medal of Excellence recipients are recognized throughout the calendar year. The 2023 Medal of Excellence Award recipients: Special Recognition: N/A Nephrologist/Physician Category: Samir K. Nangia, MD, CPE, ACC, FASN Transplant Surgeon Category: Mark D. Stegall, MD Transplant Professional Category: Vineeta Kumar, MD, FAST Nursing Category: Pamela Hoyt-Hudson, RN, BSN (Global Honoree) and Janae Thompson, RN, BSN (National Honoree) Dietetic Category: Sara Eve Schaeffer, MBA, MA, RD Dialysis Technician Category: Heather Paradis Social Worker Category: Katina Lang-Lindsey, PhD, LMSW Presidential Volunteer Service Awards AAKP is a PVSA-authorized and certifying organization and the largest organization in the kidney space that participates in this important American initiative. In 2020, AAKP launched its inaugural PVSA program, and twenty-nine kidney advocates received recognition from President Donald J. Trump for their work to educate high-risk immunosuppressed and immunocompromised kidney patients on threats posed by COVID-19. The PVSA was founded by President George W. Bush in the aftermath of the terror attacks of September 11, 2001, as one of several initiatives, including the President's Council on Service and Civic Participation, designed to encourage and exemplify the strength of outstanding American volunteerism and community engagement. The award program has continued under successive presidential administrations. The PVSA program is led by AmeriCorps (formerly the Corporation for National and Community Service), an organization whose vision originated in the administration of President William J. Clinton, and is managed in partnership with Points of Light, an organization whose vision is rooted in the administration of President George H.W. Bush. In 2022, President Joseph R. Biden recognized a number of AAKP patients and advocates with a U.S. PVSA. Six AAKP leaders received the President's Lifetime Achievement Award, the highest level of recognition that is unique and recognizes an exemplary level of volunteerism to build a stronger nation through volunteer service, including the investment of thousands of hours of personal time and professional expertise. The AAKP members who received the Presidential Lifetime Achievement Award, as well as PVSA awards at the gold, silver, and bronze levels, are nationally known advocates deeply involved in efforts to impact kidney science, innovation, and policy through collaborations with top kidney scientists, elected and appointed leaders, federal agencies, investors, major companies and startups, and nearly every major academic research center and university involved in kidney research. President's Lifetime Achievement Award: " Richard Knight (MD), former dialysis patient,16-year transplant recipient; AAKP President; Member, National Institutes of Health/NIDDK Strategic Planning Committee; Co-Chair, Community Engagement Committee, NIH/NIDDK Kidney Precision Medicine Project; Member, Scientific Registry of Transplant Recipients (SRTR) Visiting Committee; 2017 recipient, American Society of Nephrology's President's Medal; 2020 PVSA recipient " Edward V. Hickey III (CA), USMC veteran, kidney patient; AAKP Vice President; Chair of AAKP Veterans Health Initiative (VHI); Reviewer, Department of Defense Congressionally Directed Medical Research Program; AAKP liaison, U.S. Department of Veterans Affairs; Member, Judging Panel, U.S. Department of Health and Human Services/American Society of Nephrology KidneyX COVID-19 Kidney Care Challenge; 2020 PVSA recipient " Paul T. Conway (VA), former dialysis patient, 25-year transplant recipient; AAKP Chair of Public Policy and Global Affairs; Co-Chair, AAKP/George Washington University Global Summit on Kidney Disease Innovations; Member, American Board of Internal Medicine's Nephrology Specialty Board; Chair, FDA Patient Engagement Advisory Committee; Member, Observational Study Monitoring Board, National Institutes of Health/NIDDK Kidney Precision Medicine Project; 2017 recipient, American Society of Nephrology's President's Medal; 2020 PVSA recipient " Suzanne Ruff (NC), living organ donor; author, The Reluctant Donor; freelance writer, Charlotte Observer; AAKP National Board of Director and National Ambassador; 2020 PVSA recipient " Dr. Stephen Fadem (TX), patient, Clinical Professor of Medicine, Baylor College of Medicine, Section of Nephrology; Chair, AAKP Medical Advisory Board; AAKP Life Member; Recipient, AAKP's Samuel J. Orenstein and Peter Lundin, MD Awards; AAKP Historian; recipient of AAKP Lifetime Achievement Award; 2020 PVSA recipient " Bob Abbott (AR), caregiver; Charter Member, Arkansas Kidney Disease Commission; AAKP Life Member; recipient, AAKP Samuel J. Orenstein Award (2011); recipient, 2019 AAKP National Patient Engagement and Advocacy Award; 2020 PVSA recipient PVSA Gold Medal: " Kent Bressler, MA, RN (TX), U.S. Army veteran, pre-emptive transplant recipient; AAKP National Board of Director and National Ambassador; Reviewer, Department of Defense CDMRP; Co-founder of Kidney Solutions; and host of Kent's Kidney Stories Podcast series; 2020 PVSA recipient " Jennifer Jones (VA), USMC veteran, former dialysis patient, current transplant recipient; AAKP National Board of Director and National Ambassador; 2019 recipient of AAKP National Social Media Education and Advocacy Award; 2020 PVSA recipient " Dr. Janice Lea (GA), Professor of Medicine, Emory University; CMO, Emory Dialysis; AAKP National Board of Director; 2019 recipient, AAKP Samuel J. Orenstein Award; Principal Investigator, AAKP PCORI Engagement Awards; 2020 PVSA recipient " Dr. Dominic Raj (VA), Professor and Director, the Division of Kidney Diseases and Hypertension, George Washington University School of Medicine and Health Sciences; Co-chair, AAKP/GWU Global Summit on Kidney Innovations; 2019 recipient, AAKP Peter Lundin, MD Award; 2020 PVSA recipient " Glenda Roberts (WA), former dialysis patient; current transplant recipient; Director, External Relations and Patient Engagement, the Kidney Research Institute (KRI); AAKP National Ambassador; Member, Patient Advisory Board for Center for Dialysis Innovation; former Executive Director, Transplant House; 2020 PVSA recipient " David Rodriguez (TX), former dialysis patient, current transplant recipient; Patient Specialist, University Transplant Center San Antonio; AAKP National Board of Director and National Ambassador; member, AAKP Public Policy Committee; 2020 PVSA recipient " Dale Rogers (ID), former dialysis patient, current transplant recipient; AAKP National Board of Director and National Ambassador; member of AAKP Programs/Development Committee; AAKP Peer Mentor; 2020 PVSA recipient " Dr. Barry Smith (NY),Founder,Dreyfus Health Policy and Research Center; former President/CEO, The Rogosin Institute; AAKP National Board of Director; 2020 PVSA recipient " Dr. Jonathan Himmelfarb (WA), Co-Director, the University of Washington Center for Dialysis Innovation; Director, the Kidney Research Institute; Professor of Medicine and Adjunct Professor of Bioengineering; expert presenter, AAKP Global Summit on Kidney Disease Innovation and AAKP National Patient Meeting " Dr. William Fissell (TN), Medical Director, The Kidney Project; Associate Professor of Clinical Medicine, Vanderbilt University Medical Center; AAKP Medal of Excellence Award recipient; expert presenter, AAKP Global Summit on Kidney Disease Innovation, AAKP National Patient Meeting, and AAKP Policy Summit; profile feature, AAKP Innovator series " Dr. Shuvo Roy (CA), Technical Director, The Kidney Project; Professor, Departments of Bioengineering and Therapeutics Sciences and Surgery; 2021 KidneyX Artificial Kidney Prize Winner; AAKP Medal of Excellence Award recipient; expert presenter, AAKP Global Summit on Kidney Disease Innovation, AAKP National Patient Meeting, and AAKP Policy Summit</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>Program Service Accomplishments Line 4c: Patient Information and Education</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>PVSA Silver Medal: " Melissa Bensouda (TX), former transplant recipient, current home hemodialysis patient; AAKP National Ambassador; 2020 PVSA recipient " Dr. Muralidharan Jagadeesan (DC), Associate Professor of Medicine, the Division of Renal Diseases and Hypertension and Chairman of Transplant Medicine; Medical Director, Kidney-Pancreas Transplant Program at the George Washington School of Medicine and Health Sciences; Faculty and Planning Committee Member, AAKP/GWU Global Summit on Kidney Innovations; 2020 PVSA recipient " Katina Lang-Lindsey, PhD, LMSW (AL), former dialysis patient, current transplant recipient; Assistant Professor, A&amp;M University; AAKP National Ambassador; 2020 recipient, AAKP Patient Safety Award; 2020 PVSA recipient " Dammeon Marshall, MSW (GA), MSW; kidney disease patient; self-employed/entrepreneur; AAKP National Ambassador; 2020 PVSA recipient " James Myers (IN), former dialysis patient, current transplant recipient; AAKP National Board of Director and National Ambassador; Chair, AAKP Strategic Communications Committee; Chair, AAKP Pediatric Kidney Pals Initiative; 2015 recipient, Inaugural AAKP National Social Media Education and Advocacy Award; 2020 PVSA recipient " Sharron Rouse (MD), former dialysis patient, current transplant recipient; AAKP National Ambassador; Founder, Kindness for Kidneys International; 2020 recipient, AAKP Support Group of the Year Award; Co-Chair, 2020 AAKP National Patient Meeting; AAKP Peer Mentor; 2020 PVSA recipient " Lana Schmidt, MBA (IL), former home hemodialysis patient, current transplant recipient; AAKP National Board of Director and National Ambassador; Member, AAKP Strategic Communications Committee; 2020 PVSA recipient PVSA Bronze Medal: " Catherine Campbell, DNP, RN, MBA, CHC, CCM, FACHE (TX), pre-emptive transplant recipient; AAKP National Board of Director and National Ambassador; Member, the Patient Engagement and Return of Results Committee and Community Advisory Board Committee for the National Institutes of Health Kidney Precision Medicine Project; Working Group Member, International T Cell-Mediated Rejection Project " Sara Eve Schaeffer, MBA, MA, RD (FL), AAKP National Board of Director; VP, Strategic Operations, Healthmap Solutions; former Executive Director, the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services' kidney contracts for Health Services Advisory Group " Shameka Ausborn (FL), former transplant recipient, current home hemodialysis patient; AAKP National Ambassador; AAKP Peer Mentor " Gitthaline "Candie" Gagne (PA), former dialysis patient, current transplant recipient; AAKP National Ambassador; Retired Navy Hospital Corpsman; Certified Surgical Technologist " Christine Hernandez, RN, BSN (IL), registered nurse, current in-center hemodialysis patient; AAKP National Ambassador " Terry Litchfield (WI), former caregiver to husband who was a long-term dialysis patient; AAKP National Ambassador " Roberta "Bobbie" Reed (PA), caregiver to son who is a transplant recipient; AAKP National Ambassador " Cecilia Santana (NY), former dialysis patient, current transplant recipient; AAKP National Ambassador; AAKP Peer Mentor; Wellness Ambassador, The Rogosin Institute " Mihi Wickramasinghe (CA), former transplant recipient, current peritoneal dialysis patient; AAKP National Ambassador " Leigh-Ann Williams (LA), current home hemodialysis patient; AAKP National Ambassador</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>Form 990, Part VI, Section B, line 11b</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>The Form 990 is reviewed in detail by the Finance Committee. The Finance Committee approves the return. Copies of the Form 990 are provided to all Board members prior to the return being filed..</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>Form 990, Part VI, Section B, line 12c</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>All members of the Board of Directors and employees of the organization receive a copy of the conflict of interest policy. The Executive Director and all Board members are required to complete and sign a written statement that they have been and are in compliance with this policy.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>Form 990, Part VI, Section B, line 15a</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>The Executive Committee conducts an annual review of the Executive Director's performance and recommends any adjustment to salary to the Board of Directors. The Board of Directors approves raises for the Executive Director and approves the overall salary levels for all employees.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>Form 990, Part VI, Section C, line 18</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>The Form 990 is reviewed in detail by the Executive Director, Director of Office Operations, Contract CFO, and Officers. The Officers are responsible for final approval of the return. Copies of the Form 990 are provided to all Board members prior to the return being filed. The Final 990 and Audit is made available on the organization's website.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>Form 990, Part VI, Section C, line 19</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>The Final 990 and Audit is made available on the organization website.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>Program Service Accomplishments Line 4d</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>AAKP Center for Patient Research and Education AAKP firmly believes, as research has also shown, that patient and family member/caregiver education is an integral part of treatment and enhancing quality of life. Not educating a patient and their care partner about their condition and treatment options leaves the patient at risk for complications as well as the possibility of not selecting a course of treatment best suited for them. Education is a simple and effective way to improve overall health and achieve better outcomes. In the same vein, AAKP is uniquely positioned to ensure the patient has a central role in research and other activities that are designed to determine optimal approaches and strategies for providing healthcare services, assistance programs, access to new products and services, etc. AAKP constituents represent all ages, modalities, ethnicities, disease states, and a variety of demographic indicators. AAKP's research capabilities have grown rapidly, and the Association has created a sophisticated database and expansive social media channels which allow AAKP to better connect and learn from its constituents. In turn, AAKP provides education to patients and caregivers on what it means to be involved in research initiatives as well as opportunities to get involved. From online surveys, interviews, focus groups, and clinical trial awareness campaigns - AAKP is focused on inserting important patient insight and preferences into research to help inform innovation, advance care and make a meaningful impact to improve lives - this means AAKP members are helping shape the future policies and discoveries that characterize kidney care! AAKP is known within the renal community as a leader in quality education; taking time to produce programs and materials that are current, relevant and address the most pressing issues patients and their families face. AAKP is deliberate in its development of educational programs, working closely with its Medical Advisory Board, health educators and fellow patients to create unbiased, reliable resources that are easily understood and beneficial to patients. AAKP routinely uses matrices to measure program outcomes to assess effectiveness and success as well as opportunities for enhancement. AAKP offers its programs in a variety of mediums to ensure we reach as many patients as possible (print, online/web-based, smart devices, live/in-person). Research and Engagement: As a leading voice in the patient community, AAKP is uniquely positioned to assist companies interested in understanding the patient experience by connecting them directly to the thousands of patients, family members and caregivers in our database. AAKP's propriety database and engaged community of patients, creates a valuable resource to companies targeting the kidney patient population for market research and/or raising awareness on clinical trial opportunities. AAKP National Patient Meeting: The AAKP National Patient Meeting is the largest gathering of kidney patients and their care-partners in the U.S. Due to the Coronavirus pandemic, and for the safety of the AAKP professional team, speakers and audience (comprised of fellow kidney patients, healthcare professionals and industry/Federal agency partners), the 2021 National Patient Meeting was held online. The 2021 virtual patient meeting enabled AAKP to engage its national members and furthermore a global audience. The sophisticated platform AAKP used for the meeting allowed registrants to view general and breakout sessions; engage with speakers and fellow attendees; participate in a virtual exhibit hall and engage with vendor representatives in real-time; join virtual focus groups; and much more. AAKP featured several distinguished panelists and speakers, including but not limited to renowned healthcare professionals, researchers, patient experts, industry partners, and government agency representatives. All sessions are available post-event, OnDemand, for enduring education. AAKP is committed to making certain our events, like the Annual Patient Meeting, are disseminated to the widest audience of kidney consumers and decision-makers possible. Medal of Excellence Award: The Medal of Excellence Award is the Association's highest honor for kidney healthcare professionals and is designed to elevate national and international figures who have been at the forefront of advancements in kidney care and patient empowerment. The award recognizes professionals who are committed to improving and extending the lives of all kidney patients through advocacy, research, technology and quality-driven treatments that protect patient dignity and fully align with patient aspirations. This prestigious award program recognizes a variety of professionals within the health care team including: nephrologists, transplant surgeons, transplant professionals, nurses, social workers, dietitians and dialysis technicians. Patient Safety Award: Established in 2013 by the Network of New England Board of Directors to continue the patient safety work of the nonprofit organization led by Jenny Kitsen, former AAKP Board of Director. That organization held the CMS contract for ESRD Network 1 for 35 years, from 1977-2012. The Network staff, patients and professional volunteers who supported Network activities made a number of innovative contributions to the ESRD Network Program. Under Ms. Kitsen's direction, with the Board guidance, the New England Network organization became known for its leadership in patient safety. The AAKP has accepted an endowment from the Network of New England Board of Directors to honor Ms. Kitsen. The award funds a lecture or program that advances new approaches for increasing kidney patient safety knowledge and/or the dissemination of new research pertaining to effective safety procedures among medical professionals responsible for patient safety. In 2022, AAKP granted its first international safety recognition, honoring The Renal Patients Support Group (RPSG) of the United Kingdom. The RPSG participates in the AAKP Global initiative and is part of AAKP's expanding international collaborative of patient organizations focused on patient consumer-centered policies and innovations. Additional award recipients have included: Alan Kliger, MD, Chair, Nephrologists Transforming Dialysis Safety (NTDS), American Society of Nephrology (ASN); The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention; Satellite Healthcare; National Kidney Foundation; National Renal Administrators Association; A.T. Still University of Oral Health; All Kidney Patients Support Group; Renal Physicians Association; American Nephrology Nurses Association; and the Forum of ESRD Networks. AAKP Healthline Webinars: AAKP HealthLine is a one-hour FREE webinar program educating patients and caregivers on a variety of important topics all from the comfort of their home or office. A teleconference option is available for each program should the registrant not have computer access. All HealthLine programs are recorded and archived at www.aakp.org/aakp-healthline. Webinars are hosted monthly, recorded, and archived on the AAKP website for enduring education. The archived webinars continue to be in the top five visited pages of the website. AAKP HealthLine Innovator Webinars: AAKP HealthLine Innovator is a one-hour FREE webinar program educating patients and caregivers on current research, clinical trials, or treatments all from the comfort of their home or office. A teleconference option is available for each program should the registrant not have computer access. All HealthLine programs are recorded and archived at www.aakp.org/aakp-healthline. Webinars are hosted monthly, recorded, and archived on the AAKP website for enduring education. The archived webinars continue to be in the top five visited pages of the website. AAKP Nutrition Program: " The AAKP Delicious! Series features a variety of kidney-friendly recipes for patients at all stages of kidney disease. All recipes have been carefully reviewed by renal dietitians and provide indications on what type of patient these recipes are most suited for. This recipe program has been favorably reviewed by the renal practice group of the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics. Six editions of AAKP Delicious! are available, featuring more than 100 kidney-friendly recipes. " AAKP Nutrition Counter is a pocket-sized guide that lists the nutrient values for standard portions of more than 300 commonly used foods. Nutrient values listed include carbohydrates, fat, saturated fat, protein, calorie, sodium, potassium, and phosphorus levels - dietary values that must be closely monitored in kidney patients. Patient Pocket Guides: This brochure series offers a template for AAKP to develop a number of convenient, pocket sized guides that focus on a variety of important healthcare topics that patients can keep with that list top questions to ask their healthcare</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>Program Service Accomplishments Line 4d</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>team to better understand/manage conditions. " AAKP Pocket Guide to Managing Kidney Disease: This Pocket Guide is a tool to help patients and caregivers have more effective dialogue with their healthcare teams. It includes 5 Key Questions to Ask your Doctor/Medical Specialist, as well as additional questions for each stage of Chronic Kidney Disease. " AAKP Pocket Guide to Managing High Potassium: The Pocket Guide is a tool to help kidney patients and caregivers have more effective dialogue with their healthcare teams about the risks associated with high potassium levels and the best way to manage it. " AAKP Pocket Guide to Managing Chronic Kidney Disease Associated Pruritus: The Pocket Guide is a tool to help kidney patients and caregivers have more effective dialogue with their healthcare teams about Chronic Kidney Disease Associated Pruritus (CKD-aP), moderate to severe itching associated with dialysis, and the best way to manage it. " Understanding the Food Nutrition Label: The Pocket Guide is a tool to help kidney patients and caregivers have a better understanding of how to read and understand food nutrition labels to support kidney-friendly eating. " Conversation Starter: Questions to Ask Your Healthcare Team About Changing Dialysis Therapies " Conversation Starter: Questions to Ask Your Healthcare Team About Choosing the Right Therapy for You! Coping, Living, and Thriving with Kidney Disease: The purpose of this booklet is to empower individuals to take charge of their disease management by confronting negative feelings and providing strategies on how you and your team can thrive and become the warrior you want to be on this journey of kidney disease. "Understanding" Series: This workbook series covers a variety of important topics such as: Hemodialysis Options, Access Options, PD Options, Home Hemodialysis, Anemia, Iron, Depression, Fabry Disease, Hepatitis C, Kidney Transplantation, Gout, Kidney Stones, and Proteinuria. All brochures are available in print and online pdf. Kidney Beginnings: This workbook introduces chronic kidney disease and is designed for individuals recently diagnosed or with risk factors such as diabetes and hypertension. The various chapters address common topics for individuals with or at-risk for kidney disease such as: diabetes, hypertension, common medical test, common medications, emotional issues, diet/nutrition, exercise, employment and much more. Patient Plan Series: These four phased workbook series are designed to provide individuals with the information they need as they progress through kidney disease. The information is divided among the four books to allow a patient to advance when they are ready and learn information in a manageable way that allows for the greatest impact on behavioral changes. aakpRENALIFE: aakpRENALIFE is the official flagship magazine of the Association. Produced bi-monthly, the articles and information are educational in nature and designed to be relevant for patients regardless of stage of kidney disease or modality option. Content is made available online as well so that patients and caregivers have access to specialty articles at any time post-production. E-newsletters: are distributed monthly and cover current news and issues for individuals with chronic kidney disease, regardless of stage or modality. Cystinosis Patient Education and Activity Scholarship Program: While a variety of factors may cause an individual to be diagnosed with kidney disease, genetic and rare causes can be especially difficult for patients and family members to manage. Understanding the need to support individuals who have kidney diseases caused by a genetic or rare condition, AAKP has expanded its education, advocacy efforts and services to those affected. In support of AAKP's Pediatric and Rare Disease Initiatives, AAKP launched its Cystinosis Patient Education and Activity Scholarship Program for those affected with cystinosis in 2019. The objective of the scholarship program is to provide an exclusive opportunity for people living with cystinosis to provide inspiration, further their education and purse opportunities toward long-term career goals and life aspirations. This scholarship program is open to individuals diagnosed with cystinosis. Scholarship funds are available to age groups 5-17 years of age and 18+. To date, this program has funded 20 scholarships, totally over $50,000. KidneyWorks: The KidneyWorks Initiative research and policy collaboration aims to help Americans with chronic kidney disease who are not on dialysis maintain their jobs and slow their disease. KidneyWorks seeks to reduce disability and dependency and help people with ND-CKD remain active, productive, taxpaying citizens by taking proactive steps to educate patients, families, clinicians, and lawmakers and enact work-friendly practices and policies. " Phase One (Completed) Phase One included a national stakeholder meeting, preparing, and releasing a policy White Paper and Executive Summary, conducting national media rollout, and developing www.kidneyworks.org. The National Roundtable held in Washington, D.C. in June 2016 include sectors of the kidney community - patients, non-profits, professionals, members of industry and representatives from Federal government. The comprehensive KidneyWorks White Paper and Executive Summary was formally and publicly released in July 2017. The report identified barriers to patients' desire and ability to keep working and outlined a comprehensive strategy to remove them. The National Media rollout included more than 800 media websites and channels featuring KidneyWorks and the White Paper, including Fox Business News and Nephrology News &amp; Issues. " Phase Two (Underway) Phase Two will use strategies identified in Phase One to develop interventions to help people with ND-CKD slow their disease progression and keep their jobs, including targeted messaging, tools and resources, telephone helpline support, and a robust database to track contacts and outcomes. " Phase Three (2022+) Phase Three will include evaluation of the impact of KidneyWorks by using the database and conducting outcomes research. Fabry Disease Diagnostic and Education Project: AAKP and Emory University have partnered to conduct an educational research project aimed at providing free genetic testing to individuals affected and at-risk for Fabry Disease. The research findings will help identify markers to Fabry that in turn will allow patients affected be diagnosed earlier in the disease state and begin intervention and treatment immediately. AAKP continues to develop many educational resources such as medical articles, brochures and webinars highlighting the advancements in Fabry Disease, best practices and the project's research findings. AAKP Center for Patient Engagement and Advocacy: The AAKP has been a national leader in patient advocacy and education for over 50 years - and is the largest fully independent and patient-governed organization in the kidney ecosystem. AAKP is highly regarded across the Federal government among both career and appointed policy-makers and our influence in the Executive Branch and the U.S. Congress transfers across transitions and elections cycles due to our massive network of relationships and long-held reputation as an independent voice for patients. AAKP believes that patients and industry must be at the table together and engaged at all levels of decision-making whenever the Federal government seeks to implement wide-ranging initiatives that impact innovation and shape future access to care options for individuals affected by kidney diseases. AAKP fundamentally understands that kidney disease and the health and treatment of kidney patients pose a significant impact on the American taxpayer and the national economy. The cost of kidney disease alone invites constant and intense interest and concern within the Federal government and the U.S. Congress. The costs associated with the disease have spurred multiple Federal initiatives in the past several years designed to increase positive patient outcomes, reduce spending and increase efficiencies. The move by the Federal government to examine and re-examine many of the cost-drivers within healthcare spending, and specifically within the ESRD program, represents a key reason why AAKP is working aggressively to build our capacities to raise the independent patient voice throughout the Federal policy-making process. In order for AAKP to maintain our leadership in protecting patient interests, and the overlapping interests among allies throughout the broader kidney community including the pharmaceutical industry and providers, we intend to grow our membership numbers, advance our National AAKP Ambassador Initiative, expand our reach internationally and equip kidney patients across the globe with proven and cost-effective training and technologies that make an</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>Program Service Accomplishments Line 4d</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>impact on the policy process. The Center for Patient Engagement and Advocacy was created to leverage AAKP's increased profile and influence in the national public policy process and to expedite implementation of our national strategy to vastly expand patient involvement in the decisions impacting their health outcomes. The AAKP Center for Patient Engagement and Advocacy was created in 2014 to leverage AAKP's increased profile and influence in the national public policy process and to expedite implementation of our National Strategy to vastly expand patient involvement in the decisions that impact their health outcomes. The Center for Patient Engagement and Advocacy brings, under one focused area, all AAKP efforts to build patient and family/caregiver membership in AAKP as well as their participation in existing and emerging AAKP patient health engagement and advocacy programs. At the heart of this Center is the AAKP Ambassador Initiative, launched in 2017, the program has grown to more than 160 + Ambassadors in nearly all 50 states plus D.C. In 2019, AAKP launched the Global arm of this initiative and now has Global Ambassadors in countries such as Ireland, Canada, Argentina, United Arab Emirates and Puerto Rico. Ambassadors are AAKP's most engaged volunteers who utilize their personal experiences and professional skills to contribute to both the AAKP mission and the larger kidney community based on their desire to serve a cause larger than themselves. These individuals also allow AAKP to expand our reach and resources to make a positive impact at the state and local level and globally. Since 2018, AAKP has conducted the largest virtual kidney voter registration drive in America, the "I am a Kidney Voter" campaign, which has registered patients in every state. #IAmAKidneyVoter, #KidneyVoter. Major programs within this Center include the Decade of the Kidney, the Global Summit on Kidney Innovation, the Public Policy Summit, and the Ambassador Initiative. Additionally, as part of the AAKP National Strategy, the Center for Patient Engagement and Advocacy works to engage, train, certify and deploy kidney patients in ways that are the most effective at elevating the patient voice within Federal policy-making circles. This includes critical times when national legislation, health program implementation, regulations or potential delays in the pharmaceutical approval process pose a concern to patient access to quality care or their future healthcare outcomes. AAKP is engaging and encouraging kidney patients and caregivers to participate in substantive opportunities for effective patient engagement and advocacy. AAKP operates via key distinctives and principles: 1. Elevate patient voice in national issues and across drug, diagnostic and device development 2. Protect the unique relationship between patients and their doctors 3. Educate patients and preserve their access to choices as informed consumers of healthcare 4. Maintain full independence in all national policy and decisions - never surrender your letterhead 5. Honor the principle of "no surprises" among trusted allies and Federal government officials AAKP has a history of advocating on important issues affecting patients' care, treatment, options, medications and such. The Advocacy Program helps support initiatives such as: Capitol Hill Day visits, participation in meetings/seminars/conventions, public policy, Communication, research issues affecting patients and practical tools that explain how to be more effective advocates. The Decade of the Kidney The Decade of the Kidney is a transformative announcement AAKP made in June of 2019 at its 2nd Annual National Policy Summit in Washington, D.C. designed to unite the community around a central thought - or a "big idea." From 2020-2030, during the Decade of the Kidney, we will see even greater contributions from every sector of our society and every discipline. These include medicine, science, academia, electedofficials, industry, media, entertainment, government, the military and insights from our veteran populations. These sweeping changes will not be limited to our shores as Americans - they will incorporate the vibrant contributions of scientists, researchers and clinicians around the world whose achievements are moving us closer to addressing the toughest kidney diseases. As patients we know that kidney disease affects people everywhere - it does not discriminate, it knows no political affiliation and it recognizes no border. To accelerate change, AAKP believes that a far larger strategic context and message is needed to unite a broader base of Americans and far more communities behind ongoing efforts to fight kidney disease and give hope to the 40 million Americans who suffer from kidney diseases. We believe that the Decade of the Kidney will do precisely that - help explain to the general public and national policy leaders that each of our singular efforts and innovations underway in kidney disease are in fact part of a far larger national effort to save and improve lives for those who suffer from kidney disease - and those yet to be diagnosed. AAKP recommitted itself to this original formula and strategy to gain new national relevance; exponentially greater engagement and growth among kidney patients and their families; and far greater influence to push for greater patient choice and more innovative care options for patients. Working together, AAKP and its members and allies have achieved profound impacts in the past several years - including legislation that allows HIV to HIV organ transplants, lower prescription drug costs and, most recently, AAKP contributed to the White House Executive Order on Advancing American Kidney Health and the Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) initiatives to fight kidney disease. AAKP also believes that by uniting all sectors of the kidney community under one strategic theme - it will be far easier to secure additional media and grassroots support, national research funding and public understanding for kidney disease. Global Summit on Kidney Disease Innovation The Global Summit is a two-day event in Washington, D.C. designed to engage the top international experts in the field of kidney care including healthcare professionals, academics, government leaders and regulators, industry experts, entrepreneurs, and patient advocates. This event is a partnership of the George Washington University School of Medicine, one of the top medical schools in the nation with an internationally recognized kidney care program, and the American Association of Kidney Patients (AAKP), the oldest and largest fully independent kidney patient organization in the United States. The 2020 Global Summit hosted virtually in response to the Coronavirus pandemic, highlights include: Over thousands of registrants, 20 special medical and patient expert sessions, 5 countries represented by speakers, and 70 countries reached via the live stream. Panel presentations and discussions were recorded and made available OnDemand on the AAKP website for enduring education. Speakers Bureau The AAKP Speakers Bureau, under the AAKP Center for Patient Engagement and Advocacy, provides the public, private sector companies and non-profit organizations with highly knowledgeable experts committed to advancing the AAKP mission through personal experiences and expertise. Speakers include AAKP National Board Members and National Ambassadors. Each speaker is well-prepared to talk before large and small audiences. Together, our speakers share a wide range of disease and treatment experiences, and their combined professional portfolios include published articles and books, participation in key government initiatives, industry focus groups and clinical trials, and testimony before Federal agencies. The AAKP Speakers Bureau is AAKP's contribution to the growing movement to generate greater public understanding of kidney disease nationwide, from local towns to the corridors of government in our nation's capital. AAKP Veterans Health Initiative The AAKP Veterans Health Initiative (VHI), based within the AAKP Center for Patient Engagement and Advocacy, is designed to advance research, innovation and policies aimed at safeguarding the highest standards in kidney care and treatment for veterans managing kidney disease both inside and outside the VA medical system. AAKP utilizes sophisticated social media and grassroots technologies to engage patients, medical professionals, and the public and to voice their concerns among policymakers. Veterans and their families face many unique challenges related to managing their healthcare and this is especially true for veterans who suffer from kidney and other complex, chronic diseases. AAKP is committed to making its fellow veterans have their voice heard, retain access to the care they have earned and are legally entitled to at the VA and elsewhere and gain the benefit of</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>Program Service Accomplishments Line 4d</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>new research and innovations in the realms of biologics, diagnostics, and devices. In 2023, the AAKP announced a formal partnership with the Veterans Health Administration (VHA) Kidney Disease Program. Capitol Hill Day Visits: These educational visits, hosted virtually in 2022-23, engage patients, care partners and healthcare professionals with their legislative representatives and staff to discuss current policy issues that affect patient care and quality of life. Participants are provided training on how to conduct respectful and substantive meetings before ever visiting Capitol Hill. AAKP also partners with medical professional organizations when policy issues related to patient services overlap with our strategic issue agenda. These organizations include, but are not limited to the following: " Alliance for Home Dialysis " Alport Syndrome Foundation " American Kidney Fund " American Society of Nephrology " American Society of Pediatric Nephrology " American Society of Transplantation " American Society of Transplant Surgeons " Kidney Community Hill Day (a collaborative effort of over twelve national organizations) " Kidney Health Initiative " Medical Education Institute " National Kidney Foundation " National Renal Administrators Association " PKD Foundation " Renal Physicians Association " TransplantFirst Academy, and more. Contact AAKP for a full list of partners. In 2022-23, AAKP has conducted over 600 Hill visits, independently and jointly with key allied organizations. AAKP's Ambassador Initiative: The AAKP Ambassador Initiative is part of our Center for Patient Engagement and Advocacy. Ambassadors are our most engaged volunteers - seasoned experts on kidney disease, dialysis, transplant, and living kidney donation. Ambassadors utilize their personal experiences and professional skills to contribute to both the AAKP mission and the larger kidney community based on their desire to serve a cause larger than themselves. AAKP helps provide Federal officials with the patient input they seek, through our Ambassadors' engagement. Ambassadors maintain relationships and communications with their elected leaders to be sure kidney disease is on their radar. They participate in focus groups, roundtables, Technical Evaluation Panels (TEPs), surveys, clinical trials, public testimony before Federal agencies, and more. Throughout 2021-22, AAKP expanded this initiative to include International Ambassadors from countries including, but not limited to: Argentina, United Kingdom, Ireland, United Arab Emirates, Germay, and Canada. AAKP Policy Summit: AAKP is a nationally recognized leader in patient education and advocacy and our independent insights are highly regarded and relied upon by government agencies, elected and appointed national policymakers and policy influencers. With 50 years of effective patient engagement experience, AAKP knows that patients, government, researchers, professionals and industry working collaboratively together is the fastest way to transplant new innovations in kidney care into care solutions that impact patient health outcomes. The Policy Summit brings together key influencers from across all sectors of the policy spectrum for a two-day Summit that addresses the current state of kidney care at the crossroads of innovation, regulation, and payment. AAKP Policy Roundtable: AAKP Policy Roundtables focus on timely and critical issues impacting kidney care. Strategic Partnerships and Alliances: AAKP has maintained our national reputation as a trusted and independent voice for patients by both maintain our independence and through a select and targeted series of collaborative relationships with other non-profit professional and patient organizations. Before AAKP collaborates with any organization, we pose several questions to assess their credibility in our order to protect our organization and the patient interests we represent. These questions include: 1. Will our association with this organization discredit the AAKP mission and legacy? 2. Will our association with this organization confuse or contradict the AAKP message? 3. Will our association with this organization turn away potential long-term allies? 4. Will our association with this organization discourage elected/career policy-maker interest or support of policy goal? 5. Will our association with this organization fulfill a negative narrative already underway about your issue/community? Our current strategic partnerships and alliances include but are not limited to: " Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics " Alliance for Home Dialysis " Alport Syndrome Foundation " Alliance for Gout Awareness " Alliance for a Stronger FDA " American Kidney Fund " American Nephrology Nurses Association " American Society of Nephrology " American Society of Pediatric Nephrology " American Society of Transplant Surgeons " American Society of Transplantation " Dialysis Clinic, In. " Emory University " ESRD Rockstars " For Kidney's Sake, Inc. " Forum of ESRD Networks " Friends of NIDDK " Friends of HRSA " Home Dialyzers United " IGA Nephropathy Foundation of America " International Home Dialysis Roundtable " Kaiser Permanente GA " Kidney Health Initiative " Making Dialysis Safer Coalition " Medical Education Institute " National Association of Nephrology Technicians " National Kidney Foundation " National Renal Administrators Association " National Psoriasis Society " NephCure Kidney International " Oxalosis and Hyperoxaluria Foundation " Patient Access to Pain Relief (PAPR) " Patient Alliance for Drug Safety Protections " Polycystic Kidney Disease Foundation " Precision Medicine Coalition " ReMend " Renal Pathology Society " Renal Physicians Association " Renal Support Network " Rogosin Institute " Scientific Registry of Transplant Recipients " Society of Transplant Social Workers " Southeastern Kidney Transplant Coalition " TRIO - Transplant Recipients International Organization " Veterans Transplant Association, and more. Contact AAKP for a full list of partners. Federal Agency Engagement: Over the course of the past year, and again as a result of our national engagement strategy, AAKP has been heavily involved with multiple Federal agencies. AAKP has traditionally worked very closely with Federal agencies since our organization leads national efforts to establish the End Stage Renal Disease Program (ESRD), administered since 1973 by Department of Health and Human Services under the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services (CMS). AAKP values the civil service of the United States and has maintained strong relationships with programs, agencies and personnel under every Presidential Administration since 1973 and is non-partisan in our engagements with the U.S. civil service. Below are just a few of the agencies AAKP engaged with: " Center for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) " White House Office of Science and Technology Policy (OSTP) " White House, National Economic Council (NEC) " U.S. Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) " U.S. Department of Labor (DOL) " U.S. Department of Defense (DoD) " DOL/Office of Disability Employment Programs (ODEP) " HHS/Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Assistance (CMS) " HHS/Center for Medicare and Medicaid Innovation (CMMI) " HHS/Food and Drug Administration (FDA) " HHS/National Institutes of Health (NIH) " HHS/National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK) " HHS/Health Resources and Services Administration (HRSA) " Veteran's Administration (VA) In addition to these agency engagements, AAKP has served as the Chair of the CMS Technical Evaluation Panel (TEP) for the CMS Dialysis Facility Compare 5 Star Rating Program as well as multiple other TEP's. AAKP also holds multiple seats on the Board and subcommittees of the Kidney Health Initiative - an FDA/ASN breakthrough collaborative and is actively involved as well in the Clinical Trials Transformation Initiative, another breakthrough collaborative between the FDA and Duke University. AAKP leadership holds positions within the NIH Kidney Precision Medicine Project, the FDA Patient Engagement Advisory Panel, and the CDC Healthcare Infection Control and Advisory Council.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
    </IRS990ScheduleO>
  </ReturnData>
</Return>
